<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sylvain Abélard</title>
    <description>Sylvain Abélard - talks, events, blog, projects, translations...
</description>
    <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://maitre-du-monde.fr/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 10 Dec 2016 15:38:21 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 Dec 2016 15:38:21 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.3.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Parler politique</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Indépendamment de l’article lui-même (https://vorpus.org/blog/why-does-calloc-exist/),
l’auteur s’est rendu compte que ça devenait populaire sur Hacker News,
et a commencé par une note à leur intention :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[Edit: Welcome Hacker News readers! Before we dive into the neat memory management esoterica, I want to briefly note that as engineers we have an ethical obligation in our work to consider the “safety, health, and welfare of the public”, because if we don’t, terrible things happen. This is a challenging responsibility that requires we all stay thoughtful and informed – but that’s difficult if popular technical news aggregators choose to censor links and discussions about the societal implications of technology. I sympathize with their moderation challenges, but this idea of creating a politics-free safe space is the cowards’ way out, quite literally choosing the “absence of tension” over “the presence of justice”. I hope the HN moderators find a way to step up to the responsibility their position entails; in the mean time, you might consider also subscribing to to The Recompiler and Model View Culture, and checking out Safety Pin Box, techsolidarity.org, or Fund Club. Anyway, thanks for listening! We now return to our regularly scheduled calloc-related programming, and I hope you enjoy my essay. And if you like this, you might also enjoy Cory Benfield’s related post.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outre le fait que je suis d’accord sur le principe (sans juger les publications qu’il recommande)
c’est une parfaite illustration du “take sides” du talk de @r3trofitted sur Megadeth au ParisRB du 6/12/2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nous avons une responsabilité, il a eu une vague de célébrité, et c’est un bon usage d’icelles je trouve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;J’ai envie de dire que je ne me sens pas le leader de la communauté ParisRB :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;elle se compose d’individus, et de tous ceux que j’ai la chance de connaître, ils sont généralement formidables&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;elle est vivante et produit des initiatives “à côté” comme Women On Rails, Rails Thematic Workshops et Ruby Workshops Paris&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;je ne peux pas la guider ou lui demander d’aller dans une direction “en tant que chef”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mais j’ai de la visibilité et je peux montrer mes valeurs par l’exemple.
En ces temps troublés, je ferai l’inverse de HN et &lt;em&gt;encourage&lt;/em&gt; les gens à parler politique, ici ou ailleurs.
J’aimerais toutefois que ça se fasse en bonne intelligence, pour comprendre et apprendre,
et contre les biais et moisissures argumentatives https://cortecs.org/materiel/moisissures-argumentatives/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;De fait, les mêmes peurs et constatations (peu de ressources, peur de vivre moins bien) mènent parfois à des conclusions opposées (retirez les ressources des gens différents&lt;br /&gt; augmentez la protection de tous afin que mes proches et moi-même soient toujours “sauvé” si on devait dégringoler par un hasard de la vie).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pour moi la clé est d’en parler. Je laisse le mot de la fin à Berthold Brecht :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;« Le pire des analphabètes, c’est l’analphabète politique.
Il n’écoute pas, ne parle pas, ne participe pas aux événements politiques.
Il ne sait pas que le coût de la vie dépend des décisions politiques. L’analphabète politique est si bête qu’il s’enorgueillit et gonfle la poitrine pour dire qu’il déteste la politique.
Il ne sait pas, l’imbécile, que c’est son ignorance politique qui produit la prostituée, l’enfant de la rue, le voleur, le pire de tous les bandits et surtout le politicien malhonnête, menteur et corrompu, qui lèche les pieds des entreprises nationales et multinationales. »
Bertolt Brecht, poète et dramaturge allemand (1898/1956)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/12/07/parler-politique.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/12/07/parler-politique.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Most Important Improvement</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;What is the most important thing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know, we’re all connected, everything depends on other things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is the engine the most important part of a car? Well without gas it won’t run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is the Brain the most important part of the body?
Heart beats, mouth eats, lungs breathe… take any single one away and you die.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dev skill, language or framework mastery is important?
Communication, politeness, problem discovery, social dynamics more important ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think of important things as glass panels: light shines outside,
you want to have some light inside, and we have many panels in between.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If any of these panels lets 0%~10% of light pass,
other panels can be crystal-clear, but you will live in the dark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If every panel lets 90% of light pass, but you have many layers,
you will live in the dark too.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/11/26/most-important.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/11/26/most-important.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>OOP vs FP</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Popular techs, tools and methods are &lt;a href=&quot;/2016/11/19/not-enemies.html&quot;&gt;not enemies&lt;/a&gt;.
They compete for attention and trendiness, not in codebases, workplaces, or skillsets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a fake divide between OOP and FP, and a weird divide on several methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You can use functional ideas in an OOP language/stack!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do it daily in Rails, and I got at least 50% to 80% of the FP boost
in clarity, productivity, quality, less bugs…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I do not follow the FP way “all the way” and I do not get the benefits of,
say immutability, but I don’t get the hassle too ;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Just like you can Agile + DDD + TDD + CQRS + ES + almost any stack.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are not exclusive and each will bring some of its advantages to the table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, JS is OOP but prototype-based. It’s pretty much one-of-a-kind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ruby/Smalltalk/Objective C are message-passing OOP (I call it the &lt;em&gt;Alan-Kay-OOP&lt;/em&gt; and I feel that’s the only correct one),
almost all others are/feel/are used like inheritance-OOP (I call it the &lt;em&gt;Stroustrup OOP&lt;/em&gt; or C++/Java OOP).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel that Java-OOP has problems and when you see the GoF book (design patterns: a catalogue of usual solutions).
I feel like you actually have usual problems caused by your typing system and that it’s a “language smell” you should get rid of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, you can definitely use inheritance patterns with JS or Ruby, but that makes me sad because you lose the strengths they have that I love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FP-fans are big on immutability: you set a variable, it doesn’t change.
It’s not so hard once you get the idea, and it forces you to rename variables.
No more &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;things = category.things; things = things.select(&amp;amp;:foobar)&lt;/code&gt;
But you can do &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;things = category.foobar_compliant_things&lt;/code&gt; or
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cat_things = category.things; displayable_things = cat_things.select(&amp;amp;:foobar)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the first time you &lt;em&gt;force&lt;/em&gt; immutability on people it usually is super frustrating.
But what I found I like is you tell them about the idea (awareness) then train them (education) then gradually add and fix it in your codebase…
then you can either force the immutability (reflexes are OK but you don’t want to throw all code away just to change language)
or be happy that you are already 80% of the way and continue working (while reaching 90%) :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/11/22/oop-vs-fp.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/11/22/oop-vs-fp.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Not enemies</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Popular techs, tools and methods are not enemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They compete for brain-space, attention, a spot in HN, tweets or trendy blogs.
But they do not compete in codebases, workplaces, or skillsets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As people debate fiercely about things they like,
it’s important to remind we’re not enemies, our passions are not enemies,
and when we say it’s super important, no one can say what “the most important thing” is.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/11/19/not-enemies.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/11/19/not-enemies.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>We are not managers</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As young devs, we are not managers: learn it before you need it super-badly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I dislike most management schools or classes or methods or whatever.
I almost only trust learning doing the job with great examples and mentors.
By the way, I also think this applies for becoming a dev worth any salt too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you will be young and in charge of creating a company and managing a team.
But theory doesn’t really help when a coworker gets a divorce or someone they love has cancer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life is harsh. Plan around it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And learn to be a great manager before you’re in a situation where neglecting a thing
kills your company, your safety net, your relationships…&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/11/16/we-are-not-managers.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/11/16/we-are-not-managers.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Start here, go there</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Young devs are rarely great POs/marketers.
Hell, we’re even rarely even great devs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the reverse is true:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if you start by being a dev you probably suck at marketing/business/law. It’s fine, you’re young.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if you start being a marketer you probably suck at tech (at least dev) and law, perhaps even business.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so on for every skill.
Be curious and learn at the previous jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 12 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/11/12/start-here-go-there.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/11/12/start-here-go-there.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>First prove it</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;You’ve decided to invest your safety net in creating a company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as it’s incorporated, money flows… out.
Legal obligations, time to spend for many incidental things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, try to prove your ideas: because you’re likely wrong,
and because this will help you learn what you currently lack.
This is the famed “work at night and weekends in your garage” phase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explain your ideas, try out your pitches, ideas and solutions,
see if it can “get traction”, or if anyone else is willing
to commit money, time and attention to your future product or company.
This is when you know you can get out of the garage :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are plenty of ways to test ideas in a relative safety.
This doesn’t apply to all aspects of all ideas, but at least take that advantage when you can.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/11/09/first-prove-it.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/11/09/first-prove-it.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Plan, meet enemy</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“No plan survives the contact with the enemy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When creating a company, we have explicit and implicit ideas.
And these ideas are often wrong, so our plans need to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, we need a plan.
Or perhaps more accurately, we need to set a direction,
so we can explain where we’re going and if we’re making progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hidden part is: how (and how often) do you do reality-checks
and confront your plans to actual metrics to see if you’re on track?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If creating a company is your first job, there are many cues
you don’t even know how to notice.
You probably don’t know you need to change, nor how to change, nor how to communicate efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may be too much at once. Learn other things in another job.
But make sure that’s a job where you learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So your idea will change, be open and lose that ego!
The world has plenty of ideas, but even good ideas need some adaptation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You WILL be glad to see “your” idea work.
You WILL be sad that it had to be changed so much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not about you being stupid the first time you got the idea.
It’s about not being stubborn when the World tells you you need some change.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/11/05/plan-vs-world.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/11/05/plan-vs-world.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Power Porn</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Power Porn is not the real world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s good to learn from the past.
It can be motivating to read life of successful people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But their advice is not for everyone:
Bill Gates had a rich family,
Jobs had talented friends/coworkers.
… every single one has a complex context to understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, reading biographies of inspiring men and women?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some call it “Power Porn”,
others call it “obvious in hindsight”,
others call it “they won the lottery and are telling you their numbers. These won’t work for you.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s interesting to see the philosophy of analysing problems and proposing solutions,
but remember what they’re worth. Read some of it, don’t read too much of it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/11/02/power-porn.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/11/02/power-porn.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why a startup?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;So, let’s be honest: WHY do you want to create a company?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because it’s trendy? 
Please get more information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because you’ll get rich? 
That is very unlikely, so make sure it’s not the only reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because you’ll get rich quick? 
That is very unlikely too. Also check you’re not harming people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because you hate having a boss? 
You won’t get magically free from constraints. Customers will boss you around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because you found a painful problem and/or see a great opportunity? 
Because you have an idea you want to try and see where it leads? 
Because you have a safety net, and why not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then GO FOR IT! :D&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/10/26/reasons-for-startup.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/10/26/reasons-for-startup.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
