<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sylvain Abélard</title>
    <description>Sylvain Abélard - talks, events, blog, projects, translations...
</description>
    <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://maitre-du-monde.fr/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2017 22:05:38 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2017 22:05:38 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.3.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>No trolling</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I don’t like the word “troll”, as in “internet trolling”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people use this word for many wildly different things.
As developers or philosophers, we know good naming is hard, and we know bad naming creates pain (Camus).
Please use the correct word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style&gt;dl dd { font-weight: bold; }&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2016/10/07/cynicism.html&quot;&gt;Cynicism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;You're probably being inconsiderate, or not helpful.&lt;/dt&gt;

  &lt;dd&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2017/01/10/dark-humour.html&quot;&gt;Dark humour&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;You have better things to do than being a smartass.&lt;/dt&gt;

  &lt;dd&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2017/01/09/fake-news.html&quot;&gt;Fake news (aka Lies)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Making things up for fun is cool until someone believes it&lt;/dt&gt;

  &lt;dd&gt;Harassment&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;That's simply not done.&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, you like trolling ? Do you really like calling yourself one of these things?
Are you taking pride in calling yourself something that’s definitely bad and definitely not yourself?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to be clever and provocative, please do, I love it!
But make sure you’re doing it cleverly, or you’ll be looking just like an angry idiot, or worse.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2017/01/11/no-trolling.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2017/01/11/no-trolling.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Dark Humour</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I like to laugh at absurd things, of which Life provides plenty.
I kinda like dark humour. But it’s dangerously close to pitfalls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve had more than my share of &lt;a href=&quot;/2016/10/07/cynicism.html&quot;&gt;cynicism&lt;/a&gt;,
which hasn’t led me to much good. Neither for me, nor for others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dark humour usually has the same problems: it “passively allows” for actual harm.
Some people will be as smart as you and see the snark. Some won’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other people will simply see that saying harmful things is OK.
It’s irrelevant whether they understand or not, if it’s a joke or not.
Things will escalate, and soon enough there’ll be some uncomfortable things.
Will you be able to stop them then? Will you have driven good folks out?
Where should the line be drawn?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is actually &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/How_to_Win_Friends_and_Influence_People#Fundamental_Techniques_in_Handling_People&quot;&gt;the very first tip&lt;/a&gt; in Dale Carnegie’s “how to win friends and influence people” (cheesy title, good tips).
Some biographies will stress out how some remarkable person never spoke foul of anyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a teenager, one usually don’t need to add to snarkiness and ego.
As an adult, when raising a problem, it’s better, more responsible to bring at least one solution.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2017/01/10/dark-humour.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2017/01/10/dark-humour.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fake news</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It looks like 2016 has been hectic for many.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many things happened, many debates were made, many sub-debates were added…
Much information and many comments were shared, losing many of the signal in the noise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Confusion, outrage, overreaction… this plays all too well in our
reptilian/fight-or-flight and primate/social brains:
new, shiny, loud things all over the place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also easy to lose oneself, one’s time, and one’s mental health in all this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a problem with underreaction too!
The word “normalization” was all over the place in my Twitter timeline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://duckduckgo.com/?q=we+don%27t+change+our+minds+even+with+evidence+of+the+opposite&amp;amp;t=ffab&amp;amp;ia=web&quot;&gt;all well known&lt;/a&gt; that we prefer information we already like, and disregard the rest.
So it’s not a surprise that we have &lt;a href=&quot;https://duckduckgo.com/?q=why+people+believe+fake+news&quot;&gt;a tendency to believe fake news&lt;/a&gt;. The more we are aware of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_cognitive_biases&quot;&gt;our many cognitive biases&lt;/a&gt;, the more we should fight the urges to let them rule us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As citizens, or as humans, we have a duty to others: to be informed and to act.
I feel we have a duty to look for truth, to keep a healthy skepticism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a fast-moving world, where jokes or propaganda are re-shared by people in power,
we have a duty to check the most dubious things, and not share until we check.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the burden should not be on us. Well, no one will take it, so now it is ours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press and ethics in press have always struggled: they should write what people buy,
but they should print what people don’t want printed (“or it’s not press but PR”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And by the way, I would have said the previous quote is from Orwell.
But I checked, and there seems to be no evidence for that misattribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, well.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2017/01/09/fake-news.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2017/01/09/fake-news.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tech coaching</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Prenons une équipe de développeurs et un projet qui vont mal.
Ça va ensemble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En général, cette équipe n’a pas le temps de s’auto-améliorer ou de faire des sujets de fond.
Les personnes jouent en permanence aux pompiers sur les problèmes les plus “brûlants”.
On croit qu’on n’a pas le temps de faire des tests ou des refactorings,
donc on continue une méthode visiblement mauvaise,
et on n’essaie apparemment pas de s’améliorer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Si les chefs sont trop fermés, ou pieds et poings liés, difficile à dire.
Mais imaginons qu’ils se disent “comment pouvons-nous nous améliorer ?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certains prennent un coach, un mentor, un senior… mais embaucher c’est cher, alors on prend un consultant.
Là encore le consultant peut être mauvais, on n’étudiera pas ce cas ; imaginons que ce soit une personne formidable et compétente.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Une des parties les plus intéressantes de cette prestation… est la définition de cette prestation.
Le manager qui accepte, les “leads techniques actuels internes à la team” et le “coach / lead tech externe partiel”,
vont cadrer la prestation : argent, heures, calendrier…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;La loi de Conway nous dit que l’humain impacte la technique et réciproquement, justement par les points
que l’on organise et que l’on considère comme importants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Par exemple, j’ai testé ces 4 choses-là et ça marche super bien :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;on fait une classroom entre devs 2h par semaine&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;on va faire un point d’archi sur ce qui est dur à comprendre pour l’expliquer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;on va faire une revue de code sur un bout de code parce que telles habitudes sont horribles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;on va augmenter la couverture de test ensemble&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;L’avantage est que la charge de nouvelles choses à absorber est 1h par semaine de cours + 1h de pratique :
pas trop pénible pour les devs, pas trop handicapant pour la “vitesse” actuelle, ni trop cher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Si les devs sont réceptifs, on peut augmenter la qualité en permanence (et le coaching peut presque s’arrêter).
Si les devs sont pas réceptifs, on peut arrêter assez tôt.
Et du coup il suffit de signer pour 3 mois (12 demi-journées), ça n’est pas un engagement très cher,
et on peut reconduire si #1 ca marche + #2 les devs en redemandent.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 14 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/12/14/part-time-tech-lead.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/12/14/part-time-tech-lead.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Parler politique</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Je suis tombé sur &lt;a href=&quot;https://vorpus.org/blog/why-does-calloc-exist/&quot;&gt;cet article&lt;/a&gt;,
et indépendamment du contenu, l’auteur s’est rendu compte que ça devenait populaire sur Hacker News,
et a commencé par une note à l’intention de ce lectorat :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[Edit: Welcome Hacker News readers! Before we dive into the neat memory management esoterica, I want to briefly note that as engineers we have an ethical obligation in our work to consider the “safety, health, and welfare of the public”, because if we don’t, terrible things happen. This is a challenging responsibility that requires we all stay thoughtful and informed – but that’s difficult if popular technical news aggregators choose to censor links and discussions about the societal implications of technology. I sympathize with their moderation challenges, but this idea of creating a politics-free safe space is the cowards’ way out, quite literally choosing the “absence of tension” over “the presence of justice”. I hope the HN moderators find a way to step up to the responsibility their position entails; in the mean time, you might consider also subscribing to to The Recompiler and Model View Culture, and checking out Safety Pin Box, techsolidarity.org, or Fund Club. Anyway, thanks for listening! We now return to our regularly scheduled calloc-related programming, and I hope you enjoy my essay. And if you like this, you might also enjoy Cory Benfield’s related post.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outre le fait que je suis d’accord sur le principe (sans juger les publications qu’il recommande)
c’est une parfaite illustration du “take sides” du talk de @r3trofitted sur Megadeth au ParisRB du 6/12/2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Nous avons une responsabilité, il a eu une vague de célébrité, et c’est un bon usage d’icelles&lt;/b&gt; je trouve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;J’ai envie de dire que je ne me sens pas le leader de la communauté ParisRB :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;elle se compose d’individus, et de tous ceux que j’ai la chance de connaître, ils sont généralement formidables&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;elle est vivante et produit des initiatives “à côté” comme Women On Rails, Rails Thematic Workshops et Ruby Workshops Paris&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;je ne peux pas la guider ou lui demander d’aller dans une direction “en tant que chef”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mais j’ai de la visibilité et je peux montrer mes valeurs par l’exemple.
En ces temps troublés, je ferai l’inverse de HN et &lt;em&gt;encourage&lt;/em&gt; les gens à parler politique, ici ou ailleurs.
J’aimerais toutefois que ça se fasse en bonne intelligence, pour comprendre et apprendre,
et contre les biais et moisissures argumentatives https://cortecs.org/materiel/moisissures-argumentatives/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;De fait, les mêmes peurs et constatations (peu de ressources, peur de vivre moins bien) mènent parfois à des conclusions opposées (retirez les ressources des gens différents&lt;br /&gt; augmentez la protection de tous afin que mes proches et moi-même soient toujours “sauvé” si on devait dégringoler par un hasard de la vie).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pour moi la clé est d’en parler. Je laisse le mot de la fin à Berthold Brecht :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;« Le pire des analphabètes, c’est l’analphabète politique.&lt;br /&gt;
Il n’écoute pas, ne parle pas, ne participe pas aux événements politiques.&lt;br /&gt;
Il ne sait pas que le coût de la vie dépend des décisions politiques.&lt;br /&gt;
L’analphabète politique est si bête qu’il s’enorgueillit et gonfle la poitrine pour dire qu’il déteste la politique.&lt;br /&gt;
Il ne sait pas, l’imbécile, que c’est son ignorance politique qui produit la prostituée, l’enfant de la rue, le voleur, le pire de tous les bandits et surtout le politicien malhonnête, menteur et corrompu, qui lèche les pieds des entreprises nationales et multinationales. »&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Bertolt Brecht, poète et dramaturge allemand (1898/1956)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/12/07/parler-politique.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/12/07/parler-politique.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Most Important Improvement</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;What is the most important thing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know, we’re all connected, everything depends on other things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is the engine the most important part of a car? Well without gas it won’t run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is the Brain the most important part of the body?
Heart beats, mouth eats, lungs breathe… take any single one away and you die.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dev skill, language or framework mastery is important?
Communication, politeness, problem discovery, social dynamics more important ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think of important things as glass panels: light shines outside,
you want to have some light inside, and we have many panels in between.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If any of these panels lets 0%~10% of light pass,
other panels can be crystal-clear, but you will live in the dark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If every panel lets 90% of light pass, but you have many layers,
you will live in the dark too.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/11/26/most-important.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/11/26/most-important.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>OOP vs FP</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Popular techs, tools and methods are &lt;a href=&quot;/2016/11/19/not-enemies.html&quot;&gt;not enemies&lt;/a&gt;.
They compete for attention and trendiness, not in codebases, workplaces, or skillsets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a fake divide between OOP and FP, and a weird divide on several methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You can use functional ideas in an OOP language/stack!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do it daily in Rails, and I got at least 50% to 80% of the FP boost
in clarity, productivity, quality, less bugs…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I do not follow the FP way “all the way” and I do not get the benefits of,
say immutability, but I don’t get the hassle too ;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Just like you can Agile + DDD + TDD + CQRS + ES + almost any stack.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are not exclusive and each will bring some of its advantages to the table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, JS is OOP but prototype-based. It’s pretty much one-of-a-kind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ruby/Smalltalk/Objective C are message-passing OOP (I call it the &lt;em&gt;Alan-Kay-OOP&lt;/em&gt; and I feel that’s the only correct one),
almost all others are/feel/are used like inheritance-OOP (I call it the &lt;em&gt;Stroustrup OOP&lt;/em&gt; or C++/Java OOP).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel that Java-OOP has problems and when you see the GoF book (design patterns: a catalogue of usual solutions).
I feel like you actually have usual problems caused by your typing system and that it’s a “language smell” you should get rid of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, you can definitely use inheritance patterns with JS or Ruby, but that makes me sad because you lose the strengths they have that I love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FP-fans are big on immutability: you set a variable, it doesn’t change.
It’s not so hard once you get the idea, and it forces you to rename variables.
No more &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;things = category.things; things = things.select(&amp;amp;:foobar)&lt;/code&gt;
But you can do &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;things = category.foobar_compliant_things&lt;/code&gt; or
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cat_things = category.things; displayable_things = cat_things.select(&amp;amp;:foobar)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the first time you &lt;em&gt;force&lt;/em&gt; immutability on people it usually is super frustrating.
But what I found I like is you tell them about the idea (awareness) then train them (education) then gradually add and fix it in your codebase…
then you can either force the immutability (reflexes are OK but you don’t want to throw all code away just to change language)
or be happy that you are already 80% of the way and continue working (while reaching 90%) :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/11/22/oop-vs-fp.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/11/22/oop-vs-fp.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Not enemies</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Popular techs, tools and methods are not enemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They compete for brain-space, attention, a spot in HN, tweets or trendy blogs.
But they do not compete in codebases, workplaces, or skillsets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As people debate fiercely about things they like,
it’s important to remind we’re not enemies, our passions are not enemies,
and when we say it’s super important, no one can say what “the most important thing” is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, they will probably end up competing for attention and trendyness in your
bosses’ minds, company strategy, buying constraints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not about tech, this is about making your company’s decisions more rational.
A key part of this is having clear, accessible information that people actually refer to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Playing the distraction game might help in the short term.
It will help future irrational decisions, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t hate the players, but change the game.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/11/19/not-enemies.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/11/19/not-enemies.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>We are not managers</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As young devs, we are not managers: learn it before you need it super-badly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I dislike most management schools or classes or methods or whatever.
I almost only trust learning doing the job with great examples and mentors.
By the way, I also think this applies for becoming a dev worth any salt too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you will be young and in charge of creating a company and managing a team.
But theory doesn’t really help when a coworker gets a divorce or someone they love has cancer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life is harsh. Plan around it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And learn to be a great manager before you’re in a situation where neglecting a thing
kills your company, your safety net, your relationships…&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/11/16/we-are-not-managers.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/11/16/we-are-not-managers.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Start here, go there</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Young devs are rarely great POs/marketers.
Hell, we’re even rarely even great devs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the reverse is true:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if you start by being a dev you probably suck at marketing/business/law. It’s fine, you’re young.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if you start being a marketer you probably suck at tech (at least dev) and law, perhaps even business.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so on for every skill.
Be curious and learn at the previous jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 12 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/11/12/start-here-go-there.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/11/12/start-here-go-there.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
