<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sylvain Abélard</title>
    <description>Sylvain Abélard - talks, events, blog, projects, translations...
</description>
    <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://maitre-du-monde.fr/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2016 21:42:49 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2016 21:42:49 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.2.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>First prove it</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;You’ve decided to invest your safety net in creating a company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as it’s incorporated, money flows… out.
Legal obligations, time to spend for many incidental things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, try to prove your ideas: because you’re likely wrong,
and because this will help you learn what you currently lack.
This is the famed “work at night and weekends in your garage” phase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explain your ideas, try out your pitches, ideas and solutions,
see if it can “get traction”, or if anyone else is willing
to commit money, time and attention to your future product or company.
This is when you know you can get out of the garage :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are plenty of ways to test ideas in a relative safety.
This doesn’t apply to all aspects of all ideas, but at least take that advantage when you can.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/11/09/first-prove-it.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/11/09/first-prove-it.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Plan, meet enemy</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“No plan survives the contact with the enemy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When creating a company, we have explicit and implicit ideas.
And these ideas are often wrong, so our plans need to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, we need a plan.
Or perhaps more accurately, we need to set a direction,
so we can explain where we’re going and if we’re making progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hidden part is: how (and how often) do you do reality-checks
and confront your plans to actual metrics to see if you’re on track?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If creating a company is your first job, there are many cues
you don’t even know how to notice.
You probably don’t know you need to change, nor how to change, nor how to communicate efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may be too much at once. Learn other things in another job.
But make sure that’s a job where you learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So your idea will change, be open and lose that ego!
The world has plenty of ideas, but even good ideas need some adaptation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You WILL be glad to see “your” idea work.
You WILL be sad that it had to be changed so much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not about you being stupid the first time you got the idea.
It’s about not being stubborn when the World tells you you need some change.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/11/05/plan-vs-world.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/11/05/plan-vs-world.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Power Porn</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Power Porn is not the real world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s good to learn from the past.
It can be motivating to read life of successful people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But their advice is not for everyone:
Bill Gates had a rich family,
Jobs had talented friends/coworkers.
… every single one has a complex context to understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, reading biographies of inspiring men and women?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some call it “Power Porn”,
others call it “obvious in hindsight”,
others call it “they won the lottery and are telling you their numbers. These won’t work for you.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s interesting to see the philosophy of analysing problems and proposing solutions,
but remember what they’re worth. Read some of it, don’t read too much of it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/11/02/power-porn.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/11/02/power-porn.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why a startup?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;So, let’s be honest: WHY do you want to create a company?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because it’s trendy? 
Please get more information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because you’ll get rich? 
That is very unlikely, so make sure it’s not the only reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because you’ll get rich quick? 
That is very unlikely too. Also check you’re not harming people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because you hate having a boss? 
You won’t get magically free from constraints. Customers will boss you around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because you found a painful problem and/or see a great opportunity? 
Because you have an idea you want to try and see where it leads? 
Because you have a safety net, and why not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then GO FOR IT! :D&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/10/26/reasons-for-startup.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/10/26/reasons-for-startup.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mind your motivation</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Creating a company is hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I already suggest to mind your body and heart:
if the machine doesn’t work, your company won’t work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way I suggested was to take two 2-year jobs to learn, earn cash, and create a network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here’s the catch: in these 4 years, many things can happen.
You might not want to create a company after that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you found happiness in other ways, and that’s fine.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you have many more constraints than expected, and that’s fine.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you got soft, in a comfort zone you don’t want to leave from, and that’s too bad.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changing jobs changes many things: location/commute, responsibilities, relationships…
If that’s your first job, it’s even going from student to employed: even more changes!
I wrote these posts for young entrepreneurs, so I’ll probably add things that happen
and change your life drastically: significant others, habits in life…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll be settling for a new rythm, and you might not create your business after that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re happy where you are and stop wanting to create a company, so be it!
I will certainly not be the judge of what makes you happy or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some will even find in their current job the challenges
which made them want to create a company in the first place. Great!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re stuck with student debt and mortage, well, that’s life.
It means it would have been dangerous to create a business, for a reason that didn’t depend on you.
There are plenty of things you can do to pay for that debt faster:
learn more, put safety nets, try things… these are great things to learn!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But you can just be stuck in habits that formed, that don’t make you happier,
and that you will likely not reconsider often. You got too soft and comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get out that comfort zone! You had dreams, act on them!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 22 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/10/22/mind-your-motivation.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/10/22/mind-your-motivation.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ça agace les devs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;J’ai lu &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.developpez.net/forums/d1606531-3/general-developpement/debats-developpement-best-of/trolldi-qu-agace-plus-tant-developpeurs/#post8774266&quot;&gt;
ce sondage sur Développez.net&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;/2016/10/20/developpez-net.html&quot;&gt;je suis un peu developpez.net, vous devriez aussi&lt;/a&gt;) et je n’ai pas aimé les choix, alors je propose les miens :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Qu’est-ce qui vous agace en tant que développeur ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;mes propres limitations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;avoir des contraintes sans avoir les moyens&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;les attitudes négatives, avec lesquelles on progresse moins/pas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Les choix présentés correspondent bien à ce que je pensais en tant que junior.
C’est vraiment un manque de vision sur l’ensemble :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;qui n’aime pas les réunions ou le patron, n’a pas compris SOIT l’utilité SOIT comment convaincre. Ça s’apprend&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;qui n’aime pas les QA, les bugs ou les collègues est souvent remis à sa place parce qu’il a raté un truc. Ça arrive, ça s’évite.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depuis qu’on apprend le code, on est remis à notre place : on a mal codé, on a oublié un cas, on a mal lu la doc, mal testé, oublié un point virgule…
Pendant des années d’école et de carrière on apprend que ce n’est pas une fatalité, qu’on peut s’améliorer. Alors faisons-le.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Le plus symptômatique pour moi c’est la doc. Mais mettons-nous à la place des autres :
on s’enrage quand les outils qu’on achète et les libs qu’on utilise sont mal documentées.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pourquoi détester la doc ? Je suis heureux d’être développeur car mes “superpouvoirs” aident des gens.
Sans manuel, ça ne les aide pas, pire ça les frustre ou les coince ou leur fait faire des bêtises !
Donnez un couteau à un enfant sans expliquer à quoi ça sert, mais que ça coupe et comment s’en servir, vous ne l’avez pas aidé loin de là.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bref, sans écrire de la doc, mon travail et mes compétences sont inutiles, je suis inutile voire malfaisant.
Là encore on peut s’améliorer : meilleurs noms de variables, meilleurs libellés, messages d’erreur informatifs, reprise sur erreur…
C’est tout simplement de l’UX (Expérience Utilisateur) !&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pour moi le plus grand danger de l’informatique, c’est d’avoir des contraintes sans avoir des moyens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vous savez qu’il faut agir et vous ne le faites pas.
Vous voulez la qualité mais vous n’avez pas le temps.
Vous voulez le temps mais vous n’avez pas l’argent pour ça.
Vous voulez aider les utilisateurs mais vous ne les rencontrez pas.
Vous voulez une équipe de qualité mais vous ne savez/pouvez pas les recruter/attirer/garder.
Vous voulez que le projet soit un succès mais vous n’avez que les on-dit de quelqu’un et vous ne savez pas qui évaluera le succès et comment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Il y a toujours quelqu’un qui édicte les règles, et qui n’a pas pensé que c’était incohérent voire anti productif.
Ce n’est même pas sa faute ! Je lui pardonne aussi ! Mais il faut pouvoir l’identifier, le dire, et changer la règle si nécessaire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Et enfin, si vous avez une attitude négative… vous passerez à côté de tout cela, et vous préférerez dire “la doc c’est chiant” que “je veux gagner ma vie en profitant de mes superpouvoirs durement acquis, pour aider les gens à gagner des superpouvoirs facilement”.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/10/21/dangers-devs.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/10/21/dangers-devs.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>developpez.net</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Je suis un peu developpez.net, vous devriez aussi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On peut reprocher que c’est un site, un look et des technos un peu vieillissants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mais je cherche à me plonger exprès dans ce que je ne connais pas, pour sortir de ma bulle, de ma chambre à écho.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Et vu le contenu technique en anglais, la France n’a pas beaucoup de communautés énormes de devs.
Il est facile pour toute grosse communauté de s’enfermer dans des travers,
mais si vous voulez discuter avec des gens qui viennent potentiellement de là-bas,
il faut éviter de les fâcher, comprendre pourquoi ils pensent ce qu’ils pensent,
et comment les accompagner vers ce que vous pensez être mieux.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;C’est pourquoi devant la quasi absence de Ruby et Rails dans cette communauté, j’ai tenté de la faire vivre un peu :
pour certains, ce que j’y écrirai sera leur premier contact avec ces technos.
Essayons de rendre l’expérience agréable, non ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alors venez vous aussi, ça ne prend pas forcément longtemps et ça peut tous nous aider :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/10/20/developpez-net.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/10/20/developpez-net.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mind your body</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Eat. 
Sleep. 
Live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have fun, meet friends and family,
do your chores and earn money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your company takes 2 years before earning money, you need a safety net.
This can be yours, your parents’[1], your significant other…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But your company will not be in good health if you are not.
A dead founder is of no use to a company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] yes, the startup world is NOT meritocratic: inherited wealth &amp;amp; connections help. Life’s unfair.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/10/19/mind-your-body.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/10/19/mind-your-body.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mind your mind</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;You want to create a company. Please do! I wish you luck.
I hope your business will make you and countless others happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be bold enough that you’re not a quitter!
Be flexible enough that you’re not a fool in a Monkey Trap!
Stay alive! Eat, sleep, and get enough motivation to work every day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would be sad if it doesn’t help people, or if you fail miserably.
Here are some things to check before starting the journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be honest as to &lt;a href=&quot;/2016/10/26/reasons-for-startup.html&quot;&gt;WHY you want to create a company&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creating a company is hard, lonely work. 
You WILL be depressed and frustrated at times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You WILL face people who don’t understand (and judge you). 
We all want to belong to a group:
without family and friends’ support, the journey gets harder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still excited about creating your own business? 
Rest on it, explore these possibilities, explore others,
and if you’re still on it, well: I wish you luck :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/10/17/mind-your-mind.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/10/17/mind-your-mind.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Young entrepreneur</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I meet many people who want to be entrepreneurs.
If this is going to be your first job after internships,
I usually want to warn you about all of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those in a hurry, I’d just say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Do two jobs for two years each first, then create your company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the others, I have to go the full grandpa-advice:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be good to your heart (be happy, chase your dream, live with your values)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be good to your body (eat, drink &amp;amp; sleep well: you’ll do no good if you aren’t good)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Don’t let your energy starve (keep growing, be curious, don’t get satisfied)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why do you want to be an entrepreneur? Why this idea?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Power Porn is not the real world (read bios but make things)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your idea will change, be open and lose that ego (it started things &amp;amp; will keep you going though)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get experience &amp;amp; money, knowledge &amp;amp; network, trust &amp;amp; proof first&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You don’t even know what you don’t know, clear some of that first&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Managing humans is hard, learn it before you need it super-badly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blog posts to come!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/10/15/young-entrepreneur.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/10/15/young-entrepreneur.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
