<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sylvain Abélard</title>
    <description>Sylvain Abélard - talks, events, blog, projects, translations...
</description>
    <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://maitre-du-monde.fr/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2015 22:05:21 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2015 22:05:21 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>HADOPI</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Je n’ai pas compris le manque d’outrage contre HADOPI.
La loi est compliquée, Internet est compliqué.
Laissez-moi faire une analogie pour comprendre le souci.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Il me semble que l’électeur français aime sa voiture.
Il me semble que les radars partout ont énervé les français.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HADOPI n’est pas un radar de plus.
L’idée était un “mouchard de l’État” dans votre ordinateur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;C’est à dire : une boîte noire dans votre voiture qui,
dès que vous dépassez la limite de vitesse ou grillez un feu rouge,
même sans policier alentour, vous êtes pris et payez une amende.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ça fait peur ? Probablement pas, parce que c’est passé.
Et qu’on se prépare à faire mieux.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 15 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/03/15/hadopi.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/03/15/hadopi.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Customers startup</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The Funds startup grows with someone else’s money. That’s a dangerous game.
The Grants startup eats up the taxpayers’ money. That’s a hurtful game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Customers startup is focusing on solving problems in a way people are willing to pay for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s long, it’s hard, it needs you to rework many assumptions, and it often doesn’t grow as fast, nor look as sexy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s the only kind of startup I respect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can be solving problems people could pay for, but not in the way you put forward.
Change, or die. But you do have my sympathy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or perhaps you found a way to extract money from people while not really solving problems.
I don’t particularly like you but you’re playing a wrong game right, so, well, why not?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 08 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/03/08/the_customers_startup.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/03/08/the_customers_startup.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Grants startup</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The Funds startup grows with someone else’s money.
It’s a system that makes money out of young, hard-working, gullible cogs.
And it has money to publicize and romanticize themselves for the next generation of cogs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Grants startup is similar to the Funds startup, only with grants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, the people you’re scamming or hurting are the taxpayers. Which is, everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The people you’re courting are the governments, which are often clueless:
- if you’re doing a great thing, they probably don’t have a structure that allows them to recognize that
- if you’re doing a new thing, they probably are too scared or not ready for that
- if you’re just looking for easy cash from a crazy system, you’re a parasite&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Funds startups, this kind need to look sexy: for the next round, for the next laborers, or for the public.
You need to show encouragement or any form of ROI, so the money gone will not look like a total loss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accepting the government’s money comes with the responsibility to do something useful and in line with the powers in place.
So you will only be hindered in your creativity and experiments.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/03/01/the_grants_startup.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/03/01/the_grants_startup.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Funds startup</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The Funds startup wants to raise funds, and to have a nice exit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s the matter about an Exit? You’re not building for the long term.
If you want funds but no nice exit, you will give up control to people who will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s the matter about raising funds?
First, you’re losing time from your product.
Then, you are borrowing money, so you will have to pay it back.
For real, or in a scammy plot.
Last big buyers lose, and will take it out on customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not sexy to toil in those meatshops. You’re just a cog.
But that system makes money, and needs more cogs.
And it has money to publicize and romanticize themselves for the next generation of cogs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/02/25/the_funds_startup.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/02/25/the_funds_startup.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Three kinds of startups</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A startup is a company. It’s not a charity. It wants to make money.
In my mind, there are three kinds of startups, related to how they make money:
- the Funds startup
- the Grants startup
- the Customers startup&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Funds startup grows with someone else’s money.
It’s a system that makes money out of young, hard-working, gullible cogs.
And it has money to publicize and romanticize themselves for the next generation of cogs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Grants startup is quite the same as above, only with grants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The people you’re courting are the governments, which are often clueless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, the people you’re scamming or hurting are the taxpayers. Everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both these kinds need to look sexy: for the next round, for the next laborers, or for the public.
You need to show encouragement or any form of ROI, so the money gone will not look like a total loss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Customers startup is focusing on solving problems in a way people are willing to pay for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s long, it’s hard, it needs you to rework many assumptions, and it often doesn’t grow as fast, nor look as sexy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s the only kind of startup I respect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can be solving problems people could pay for, but not in the way you put forward.
Change, or die. But you do have my sympathy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or perhaps you found a way to extract money from people while not really solving problems.
I don’t particularly like you but you’re playing a wrong game right, so, well, why not?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/02/18/three_kinds_of_startups.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/02/18/three_kinds_of_startups.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>I love/hate startups</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I love the idea of startups:
- most of the philosophy: move fast, fail fast, learn fast.
- the people who want to change the world, or change the status quo.
- and I love the underdogs, perhaps that’s a french thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hate the implementation of startups:
- the arrogance, monoculture and exclusion
- the young people toiling and hurting their health, life and loved ones
- the belief that everything has to raise funds&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know the arrogance is somehow necessary: if you don’t believe hard, you wouldn’t try.
Luckily the market cures that for you: people either become more humble, or bitter.
And rarely the arrogant kind who had luck in the first place and thinks it’s his talent.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/02/11/i_love_hate_startups.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/02/11/i_love_hate_startups.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>On Structured Content</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m forcing myself to small-sized chunks of content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s also two experiments I’d like to make, linking bits of my opinions to the others:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;make their relationships obvious&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;not mixing ideas and having them as atomic as possible&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;finding myself which bits of my philosophy most shape my ideas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;finding which bits of my philosophy are most useful / explain most things&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;running a PageRank or reverse-PageRank algo on it to find the “roots” of it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suppose this requires a discipline and a lot of rework I probably won’t be able / courageous enough to make.
But it’d be nice to try, and if someone else does it I’d find it interesting and motivating :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers,&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/02/04/structured_content.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/02/04/structured_content.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Own your content</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I didn’t particularly want to make a blog, but I love to share.
So I guess it’s time I give a proper home to my content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facebook, Twitter, Google all stripped us of our content.
“Content is king”, but they have none of their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many movements propose we take back control of our data and content.
This is an experiment in just that. Join me if you care :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/01/28/own_your_content.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/01/28/own_your_content.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Blogging Ego</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In here as in life, I hope I don’t have much ego showing.
Being proud and confident is nice but ego has a tendency to show up and ruin good things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When blogs were hip I was being even more hipster by despising them. Sorry, teenage years.
On the other hand, nobody had to suffer the bad content I would have written then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I have created enough content I want to share, mostly
- talks I made at events and conferences
- translations of content I thought should be shared in french
- questions I’ve been asked enough times to structure&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;so it’s not really a blogging ego, rather a way to get back control of my content and “being the change I want to bring the world”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So for now the biggest effort I’m putting in there is just reducing posts to bite-sized chunks.
I have an horrible tendency to make things huge and ugly, so I’ll leave it at that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers,&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/01/21/blogging_ego.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/01/21/blogging_ego.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>On Intellectual Property</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I don’t believe in inviolable, enforcable Intellectual Property.
I feel people who create content for others should be able to live decently,
but that’s because I feel everyone should live decently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people write things nobody wants to read, or buy.
Most IP and legal stuff I’ve seen badly protect content that needn’t be, for the wrong reasons.
Nobody feels bad for a merchant selling rotten goods.
I’m a bad writer, so well… I have a real job.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/01/14/on_IP.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/01/14/on_IP.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
