<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sylvain Abélard</title>
    <description>Sylvain Abélard - talks, events, blog, projects, translations...
</description>
    <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://maitre-du-monde.fr/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 24 May 2015 22:43:07 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 May 2015 22:43:07 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>You&#39;re no CTO</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is my series on the &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/05/03/gullible-young.html&quot;&gt;Gullible Young&lt;/a&gt;.
I don’t mean to mock them, I’ve been one.
They’re often lovable with their dreams and energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, you’re the CTO?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re the only dev in the company, you’re not the CTO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re the developer, and someone is giving you a glittering title
so you will work for him for cheap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sorry.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/05/13/youre-no-cto.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/05/13/youre-no-cto.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>You&#39;re no manager</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is my series on the &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/05/03/gullible-young.html&quot;&gt;Gullible Young&lt;/a&gt;.
I don’t mean to mock them, I’ve been one.
They’re often lovable with their dreams and energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, you were promised a managing position?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, be grateful of course, this might be a white lie to get you in.
After all, young graduates are sought after and they’ve all been
implanted the idea that managing is great and coding is dirty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But please put your ego aside and read on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you’re a bright genius, will 50-somethings listen to you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you live, see, and manage enough crises in a company setting
so someone is confident enough to give you the lead on such situations?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or will you just be updating spreadsheets for someone more important?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you need the job and can’t do something else, that’s fine.
If you actually have enough experience (associations, internships, gigs), that’s fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But please don’t think you &lt;em&gt;deserve&lt;/em&gt; to be a manager.
No one owes you nothing until you deserved it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people fought harder than you to get here.
I’d rather give them that kind of position.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/05/10/youre-no-manager.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/05/10/youre-no-manager.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Stay late, get pizza</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is my series on the &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/05/03/gullible-young.html&quot;&gt;Gullible Young&lt;/a&gt;.
I don’t mean to mock them, I’ve been one.
They’re often lovable with their dreams and energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, you stayed very late and the company paid for pizza?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, be grateful of course, someone might care about you, and it
might be the only thing they can do within the budget the company
allows them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And perhaps you stayed late because you did some horrible mistake, or
you slacked off during the day, or you have very flexible hours, or
you’re just having fun coding when nobody’s disturbing you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re willingly spending time (not your health, this isn’t worth it)
away from your passions and your loved ones, please do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But these also are basic manners. Or a way to cut you from seeing
friends who might tell you how abusive your employer is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, be aware of what your market hourly rate is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re getting 15€ worth of dinner when you give the company four
hours at 50-100€/hour, you’re just being ripped off.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 May 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/05/06/say-late-get-pizza.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/05/06/say-late-get-pizza.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Gullible Young</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The Gullible Young are a valuable resource to the IT ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Individually they’re worth nothing, and managers like that they are so cheaply replaceable.
But as a whole they represent a workforce that’s silent and easy to abuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very simple way to keep them helpless is distracting their young minds with absurdities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Everything is an emergency!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The customer is always right!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do insane hours!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You’ll be a partner!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2015/05/10/youre-no-cto.html&quot;&gt;You’ll be the CTO!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2015/05/10/youre-no-manager.html&quot;&gt;You’ll be a manager!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;2015/05/06/say-late-get-pizza.html&quot;&gt;And they’re happy when they work very late and the company pays for pizza.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re young, a valuable life lesson is “trust, but verify”.
No one should be offended if you want to check what’s really in the job offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might rationalise your choice (Stockholm Syndrome) by some things you’re learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you’re not paid enough to be living honestly and decently, leave.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you’re not growing, have time to learn or others to compare, leave.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you don’t have time to see friends, loved ones, or do hobbies, leave.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 03 May 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/05/03/gullible-young.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/05/03/gullible-young.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Self Wiki</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This blog is also an experiment in my values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should link them all to each other, “Wikify” all these views to find
contradictions, paradoxes, and dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’d be an enlightening, probably difficult, possibly life-changing experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then it’d be interesting to run some algorithms: graph traversal,
topological sort, PageRank…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These would output what are the principles I think apply to the most
situations, or the roots of the problems and behaviours, or the ones I
hold the dearest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If something already exists for this, I’d be glad to know :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 26 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/04/26/selfWiki.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/04/26/selfWiki.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Have A Nice Day</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I believe in the power of small things done everyday.
This is the story of my Have a nice day project
in three tweet-sized chunks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There’s a feared person: never smiles or says hi, looks angry. &lt;br /&gt;
I tell them everyday ‘hello, Have a nice day!’ &lt;br /&gt;
Now they smile &amp;amp; say hi to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Cleaning employees were sad &amp;amp; silent. &lt;br /&gt;
White collar people never said hi. &lt;br /&gt;
I tell them everyday ‘hello, Have a nice day!’ &lt;br /&gt;
Now they say hi to us&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In 2003 nobody said hi in my student’s residence. &lt;br /&gt;
I told everyone I met ‘hi, Have a nice day!’ &lt;br /&gt;
Months later most people spontaneously said hi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/04/19/haveaniceday.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/04/19/haveaniceday.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mouchards de l&#39;état</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Suivant le post HADOPI et l’analogie de la voiture, un ami ajoute de
nombreux points intéressants, applicables à tous les mouchards d’état
(ou d’entreprise), leur inutilité et leur dangerosité.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poser un mouchard (comme HADOPI ou PJLRenseignement), c’est non
seulement une boîte noire qui rapporte tout au gouvernement, mais qui
en plus ne fonctionne qu’avec les voitures de certaines marques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Celui qui n’a pas la boîte noire soit a des amendes en continu, soit
est suspect, cela signifie que tout ce qui sort du cadre est anormal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Une voiture étrangère, une voiture rare, une voiture modifiée ?
Vous êtes un criminel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Si la boîte noire fonctionne mal ?
Vous êtes un criminel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pour se protéger de cela si vous êtes un honnête citoyen (ou un criminel organisé) ?
Vous trafiquez la boîte pour qu’elle envoie toujours les signaux que tout va bien.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ou si elle existe, vous utilisez la dérogation de voiture rare pour
passer les mailles du filet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Les seuls qui se feront prendre sont donc les honnêtes gens distraits.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/04/12/mouchards.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/04/12/mouchards.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Voting for lizards</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Douglas Adams, “So long, and thanks for all the fish”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“It comes from a very ancient democracy, you see…” &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“You mean, it comes from a world of lizards?” &lt;br /&gt;
“No,” said Ford, who by this time was a little more rational and coherent than he had been, having finally had the coffee forced down him, “nothing so simple. Nothing anything like so straightforward. On its world, the people are people. The leaders are lizards. The people hate the lizards and the lizards rule the people.” &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“Odd,” said Arthur, “I thought you said it was a democracy.” &lt;br /&gt;
“I did,” said Ford. “It is.” &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“So,” said Arthur, hoping he wasn’t sounding ridiculously obtuse, “why don’t people get rid of the lizards?” &lt;br /&gt;
“It honestly doesn’t occur to them,” said Ford. “They’ve all got the vote, so they all pretty much assume that the government they’ve voted in more or less approximates to the government they want.” &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“You mean they actually vote for the lizards?” &lt;br /&gt;
“Oh yes,” said Ford with a shrug, “of course.” &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“But,” said Arthur, going for the big one again, “why?” &lt;br /&gt;
“Because if they didn’t vote for a lizard,” said Ford, “the wrong lizard might get in.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 05 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/04/05/lizards.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/04/05/lizards.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Introductions</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I like sharing and learning, especially to and from passionate people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like meeting new people but wondered about what to say first.
At meetups and conferences, friends of friends, there’s a lot you don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“What do you do for a living?” is obvious and popular.
It’s a bit sad to be defined by your job: some hate it, some have none.
Some love their job but it’s a bit sad to have it be your whole personality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“What’s new? What interesting things are you doing?”
First, it can be alienating for people standing out in a crowd.
Think significant others at a conference, or with university friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried going with “what do you do or love, except your job?”
It’s pretty nice and is a great conversation opener because it’s uncommon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can set people off balance: if they are shy or introverts,
they often have a premade speech that’s proven, works good, or keeps them in control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever I felt some awkwardness, I quickly add “well, it’s fine talking about
your job, especially if you love it”. But don’t worry, they’ll tell you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they have a startup, it’s probably harder to make them shut up about it anyway ;)
(full disclosure: I was and still can be like that – sorry)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’ve settled for a weird mix I try to formulate on the spot.
The idea is “what are you currently finding interesting, what last startled you,
what uncommon thing do you love”.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 29 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/03/29/introductions.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/03/29/introductions.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Smalltalk</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As a kid, I hated chit-chat. I thought:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Why say useless things? &lt;br /&gt;
Do you feel lonely? &lt;br /&gt;
I don’t, leave me alone. &lt;br /&gt;
I’m not interested in discussing the weather!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as I grew up I understood: trying to engage in smalltalk is above
all acknowledging the recipient as a fellow human. It’s saying:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hello, I saw you and want you to know you’re not a nobody to me,
but deserve some of my time and attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still don’t see much point in discussing the weather, but I’m glad you came to me.
I hope we’ll soon find an opening to anything that’s interesting to you, me, or both!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 22 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/03/22/smalltalk.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/03/22/smalltalk.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
