<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sylvain Abélard</title>
    <description>Sylvain Abélard - talks, events, blog, projects, translations...
</description>
    <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://maitre-du-monde.fr/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 16 Oct 2016 12:07:35 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 Oct 2016 12:07:35 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.2.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Young entrepreneur</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I meet many people who want to be entrepreneurs.
If this is going to be your first job after internships,
I usually want to warn you about all of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those in a hurry, I’d just say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Do two jobs for two years each first, then create your company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the others, I have to go the full grandpa-advice:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be good to your heart (be happy, chase your dream, live with your values)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be good to your body (eat, drink &amp;amp; sleep well: you’ll do no good if you aren’t good)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Don’t let your energy starve (keep growing, be curious, don’t get satisfied)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why do you want to be an entrepreneur? Why this idea?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Power Porn is not the real world (read bios but make things)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your idea will change, be open and lose that ego (it started things &amp;amp; will keep you going though)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get experience &amp;amp; money, knowledge &amp;amp; network, trust &amp;amp; proof first&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You don’t even know what you don’t know, clear some of that first&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Managing humans is hard, learn it before you need it super-badly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blog posts to come!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/10/15/young-entrepreneur.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/10/15/young-entrepreneur.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Slackbot &quot;les gars&quot;</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Dans la communauté Slack &lt;a href=&quot;http://parisrb-slack-invite.herokuapp.com/&quot;&gt;ParisRB&lt;/a&gt;,
et chez nous, Slackbot détecte tout usage du mot “gars” et répond&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;slackbot les gars &lt;em&gt;et les filles&lt;/em&gt; \o/ (ou : tout le monde)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bien sûr le grep est simpliste et si vous écrivez vraiment “les gars et les filles”,
ou si vous parlez vraiment d’UN gars dont le genre est connu,
vous tombez dans un cas pathologique où l’intervention de slackbot semble ridicule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Et ça me convient ! Aucune regexp ne sera complète.
L’objectif est simplement de faire prendre conscience aux gens
que le langage aliénant existe, que la communauté entière aspire à mieux,
et qu’un tel langage n’est pas accepté sans mot dire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En pratique, sauf quand on cherche expressément à embêter Slackbot sur ce point,
son usage régulier est correct à 80, 90, 95% : il dénote un langage moins inclusif,
des habitudes de pensées bénignes… mais des habitudes que chacun a quand même
et sur lesquelles on peut et on devrait travailler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;C’est pourquoi je reverrai peut-être un peu la formulation, ajouterai
peut-être un lien avec des lectures, mais il est extrêmement
improbable que je le retire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bref, &lt;a href=&quot;/2014/12/31/i-have-opinions.html&quot;&gt;ce sont mes idées&lt;/a&gt;,
vous avez les vôtres, apprenons l’un de l’autre !&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mais si vous voulez jouer &lt;a href=&quot;/2016/10/07/cynicism.html&quot;&gt;l’avocat du diable ou le cynisme&lt;/a&gt;,
ajoutez rapidement quelque chose d’intéressant à la conversation,
ou je risque de ne plus jouer au tennis argumentatif avec vous très longtemps.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/10/10/slackbot-les-gars.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/10/10/slackbot-les-gars.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Cynicism</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Cynicism, Devil’s advocate, snarks &amp;amp; dark humour.
I’ve played these cards more than once in my younger years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I try not to anymore: it usually doesn’t help do whatever you intended,
alienates people, make some suffer, and opens the gate for other,
actually harmful people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are good-willed, want to share, educate and strive for greater values,
it’s easy to attack “bad people”, but you might harm others in doing so.
Please embody your greater, stricter standards and values with us,
by finding positive ways to share and educate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you can’t, I get you’re dying to show us your opinions,
I often am too, but you’ll only be adding to the mess,
and come out as less brilliant and benevolent as you certainly are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will show aggressive debate is fine, which it isn’t.
It will let other people escalate, and you’d be responsible for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will let others nitpick and sidetrack onto other paths
you didn’t want to debate on, and ultimately weakens your point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are such a good and smart person, do what other smart people do:
explain with facts and patience, build simple and logic arguments.
That will lead to more inclusive and productive conversations,
from which people will actually learn instead of rejecting everything up front.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, Twitter doesn’t have room to include disclaimers.
Yes, people will always find counter-examples and we are all biased.
Yes, some days we are more open to things we dislike, and some other days we can react violently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, it’s funny to find the one sentence to destroy an opponent on the form, not principles.
I still love provocation as jokes, or ways to explore or reframe hard topics.
But “you can laugh about everything, just not with everyone (at every moment)”.
That’s not being a coward or a flip-flopper. That’s being kind, considerate and appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So please, forgive my negativity and forgive yours,
hold me to higher standards and hold yourself too.
I look forward to discovering where we’ll go.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/10/07/cynicism.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/10/07/cynicism.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Business experiments</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Innovation has a cycle of expansion and consolidation.
Your company, teams, products and tasks can be too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am comfortable with the unknown and am often in missions to help
(new or old) projects do new things in a new way. They often are
a whole experiment in themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my “Agile” team, we’re given specifications like: I want X to do Y in such way.
I’m perfectly comfortable with that and my team is able to deliver value continuously.
When it’s “too new”, we sit down and guess, think out, hypothesise the technical answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the office in front of mine, they’re given a slightly different kind of specifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-scientific-method-specifications&quot;&gt;The Scientific Method specifications&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in context A we face problem B and solve it with C&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we will give you X weeks and Y€ to come up with a different way, likely Z&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;experiment will be used for D weeks on E% or F thousand customers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we currently pay G€ and have things work in an average time of Hhours&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;your experiment will be a success if G or H go down by at least I%
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;if it works, we plan to expand your experiment for more time/customers/contexts&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;failing that, we will revert to the old ways&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their projects look like they always work great and satisfy everyone, customers included.
Why wouldn’t they? They know exactly how things work and what improvements look like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The very fact that such a spec arrives shows the stakeholders are already OK with investment:
they have to pay to play, they know it, and they budgeted how much they could spend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So don’t try to replicate the rules, but try to ask the same questions.
It’s all about knowing your business, and making other people know the stakes too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bonus idea: have some idea log, wiki or whatever house rule so you can add:
“we have tried such and such in the past and it didn’t fork for (we guess) these reasons”.
and revisit the list from time to time: it’ll give you more ideas, and it’ll be a great
way to know if some assumptions changed and if it might be time to revisit ideas again.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 10 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/09/10/business-experiments.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/09/10/business-experiments.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Team, not company</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I always hear about “small businesses this” or “huge companies that”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;its-all-about-the-team-not-the-company&quot;&gt;It’s all about the team, not the company.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve worked AT both, FOR both. None is like the other.
The basic unit for me is the team, and set of teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s like a tree (a graph, actually) where constraints are applied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bad manager can spoil everything below them, while also inciting
higher-ups to impose even more constraints in the hopes of fixing
things, or even just understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good (great) manager can shield and reorient many things so the
teams in his responsibility, and direct communications (managers,
partners, customers, teams that have to talk to yours) can be
fully functional or happy, produces value or limits damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, layers of management do add time, and take out responsibilities and involvement.
But a fully functional chain of management with trust can do wonders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, big companies do allow for some waste to happen, and attracts parasitic behaviors.
But so do well-funded startups, or full freedom to any single person. “Trust, but verify”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, small companies with a toxic leader result in the full organisation being (able to be) toxic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, everyone wants smart leaders of smart teams, with enough challenge to be motivation,
with enough money and safety so you can experiment, leverage things and see awesome results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But please, don’t think any of these is startup-specific, or Fortune-500 only.
Understand your manager, his managers, and decide for yourself what to keep and what to change.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 03 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/09/03/team_not_company.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/09/03/team_not_company.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>When to copy/paste</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Problem: I have two things working similarly, what is the best architecture?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answer: you don’t know yet, just copy-paste and see what happens next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rationale: duplication is much cheaper than the wrong abstraction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what I suggested to an (optimistic, motivated, skilled) beginner:
&lt;em&gt;you should just copy-paste the code&lt;/em&gt; because you probably won’t reuse it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You notice that you are confused, you can’t settle on the “best” approach:
that’s because there is no way to decide on that yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copy-pasting is fast and easy to do, its dangers are known:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it settles standards: bad code will be copied&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it’s easy to copy X and replace the variable name N times, just to forget the N+1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here’s what I &lt;em&gt;guessed&lt;/em&gt; would happen: the things that look similar right now
(things like reviews, comments, scores, life cycles)  will probably turn out different:
one has more fields, one has some manager validations, one has automatic behaviours…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here’s what to keep in mind: if you happen to copy-paste this &lt;em&gt;one more time&lt;/em&gt;
then it’s a smell and you should refactor, but for now you’re probably doing
wild guesses and any modelling is good enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would hate for you to have a “super clever design” (which we can’t guess right now)
then just make complicated solutions for the new needs to fit the old cleverness:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if you find a third thing which is super-similar and you change too often: refactor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if it happens that you’ll need other things, in a similar way: refactor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if it happens that X and Y are actually different in the long run… at least you didn’t start the hard way and delivered fast :)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typical Tetris Effect!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/08/27/when_copy_paste.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/08/27/when_copy_paste.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>RailsGirls groups</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;RailsGirls teaches people to code, so we are sat at tables with computers.
You’ll have to split groups, namely: who will sit at the same table?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sit one mentor at every table, and be very clear that everyone can change tables:
this will allow people not to feel shame if they are uncomfortable with anyone,
or if they feel pressured into learning a specific topic they don’t like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many events will try to separate based on previous experience, which
looks like an easy solution, and works quite well (I don’t judge),
but I found quite difficult to get the right mix. Some key questions are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;knows programming or never programmed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;knows the Web stack (HTML/CSS/basic JS) or not&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;knows MVC (in any lang/framework) or not&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How would a “true beginner” compare to an advanced WordPress tweaker,
a systems C programmer, a PHP-without-framework developer?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I try to split by interests, and I found it helped foster a feeling
of bonding and sharing: “we’re here for the same reason, and if you
teach me things you already know I hope I can bring my perspective
from another point of view”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My four categories are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“I want to understand what the hell my coworkers are talking about”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“I have some app from friends or freelancers or agency and want to regain control of it but just touch the design”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;same as above but backend-only&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“I want to become full-fledged developers”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, you’ll notice it could be very close to “what is your context,
who are the people around you right now or in very short-term future,
and what do/will they need?”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because teaching people is helping them help others, and everyone be awesome :)&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/08/24/split-beginners-groups.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/08/24/split-beginners-groups.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>RailsGirls application form</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Here’s what I do to gather information for RailsGirls.
You might want to use it as your own starting point.
No pressure, do it your way :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;welcome&quot;&gt;Welcome&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[date, place, target audience, welcome text, code of conduct]&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[explain how you’ll use/share data, when will people hear back from you]&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[add an “other” option to most questions to get more detailed feedback]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;let-us-know-you&quot;&gt;Let us know you&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your name:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your email (we won’t spam!):&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your Twitter account if any:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You want to come to RailsGirls X as a:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Beginner (to learn)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Mentor (to teach)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Assistant (I can teach stuff but I’m no expert)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your current occupation:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your computer runs on: [Windows, Mac, Linux]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-do-you-know-what-would-you-like-to-learn&quot;&gt;What do you know, what would you like to learn&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why do you want to attend RailsGirls X? [text]&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you know HTML/CSS? [1-5]&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you know how Internet works? [1-5]&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you know how to program? [1-5]&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tell us what you’re strong at [text]&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What would you like to learn?
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;how app/web work&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;design&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;programming&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;find a job as a developer&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;teach other people&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;additional-information&quot;&gt;Additional information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you have a special diet?
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Kascher, Halal, Lactose-free, Gluten-free, Vegetarian, Vegan&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you have any other constraint we should know about?
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;that’s handicap, hearing/vision/movement, constraints and such&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 20 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/08/20/railsgirls-application-form.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/08/20/railsgirls-application-form.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Admitting failure</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There’s been a lot written on admitting failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re seen as trustworthy, since responsibility and transparency are key everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The obvious gains are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;makes you less of a liar and bragger&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;doesn’t embarrass other people with hidden failure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;makes your claims at what you succeed more believable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not hiding stuff is great too, because “one lie leads to many lies”,
and since you fucked up in the first place, and in a bad enough way
that you don’t want others to know, you probably are not the best
person to cover up the consequences alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Covering up your own bullshit will take an order of magnitude more
work than what could/should have been done in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So admitting failure is also a great boost in focus and opportunities to learn.
If you let it be.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/04/20/admitting-failure.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/04/20/admitting-failure.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>RailsGirls et mixité</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;RailsGirls Paris a commencé mixte. On m’a suggéré de changer [1], j’ai tenté, j’y resterai.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;La raison la plus évidente est celle-ci :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;45 débutantes + 5 débutants / 10 mentors = 1 mentor pour 5&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mais notre éducation favorise les hommes qui parlent fort et les femmes discrètes. Rapidement :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;5 débutants accaparent 5 mentors = 1 mentor pour 1 homme
45 débutantes / 5 mentors = 1 mentor pour 9 femmes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Je disais, par souci d’égalité, “les femmes sont prioritaires si on
manque de place, mais les hommes sont les bienvenus.”
Avec le constat précédent, cette “égalité” a un drôle de goût.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Je suis disponible pour aider tous ceux qui le demandent à monter des
RailsGirls dans leur ville. J’ai conseillé Lille, St Étienne, Marseille,
Bordeaux. Mes conditions surtout si je participe sont de faire attention
aux sponsors, et mon conseil est de faire non mixte.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] À chacun de s’éduquer sur le féminisme et les problématiques,
    mais le plus simple reste encore de se la fermer et d’écouter.
    Pour le reste, c’est simple à trouver, il suffit de lire
    avec un esprit ouvert, sans rejeter a priori, et vérifier.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/01/16/railsgirls-not-boys.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/01/16/railsgirls-not-boys.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
