<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sylvain Abélard</title>
    <description>Sylvain Abélard - talks, events, blog, projects, translations...
</description>
    <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://maitre-du-monde.fr/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 19 Nov 2015 10:48:16 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Nov 2015 10:48:16 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Now &amp; Goals</title>
        <description>&lt;style&gt;h3 { text-align: center; } &lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you know the “now page” movement?
@sivers and @practicingruby use it as a focus manifesto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I probably lacks some of the focus they say I should have, but I’m not signing it.
It’s nice to have focus, make baby steps and feel progress to keep motivation.
Bit I have concerns about losing the Big Picture and closing doors (yes that’s FOMO).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My page would rather be: Goals.
I have a few long-term goals and I sometimes manage to break them into tiny bits for now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;make-tech-more-inclusive&quot;&gt;make tech more inclusive&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;now I’m doing RailsGirls + a weekly study group, and trying to understand minorities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in the next 2 years I hope to visit schools to give the yearning for programming&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in the coming years I hope to do something for the physically disabled&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;after that, probably for the mentally disabled when possible&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and after that, perhaps some training for inmates to get a job after prison&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are opportunities I’m willing to pursue.
If you have half a plan and need a hand, I’d gladly change that order for your target audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;be-a-better-person&quot;&gt;be a better person&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;make business a better place for family constraints, worklife balance (in great progress)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;learn more languages such as german and japanese (nice progress), sign language and russian&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;learn more about psychology, sociology and education&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;share whatever I can, lower the bar for these&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;selfish-projects&quot;&gt;selfish projects&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;do sports, be more fit&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;make boardgames &amp;amp; art&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;raise a family&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;impossible-possibles&quot;&gt;impossible possibles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;fix education, society &amp;amp; the world&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;expand humanity to other planets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/11/11/now.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/11/11/now.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Forgive my negativity</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;You might notice much negativity on here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am deeply sorry, because I know it makes us all miserable, and we
would all live better days and better lives if only we were more positive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plus, I know not everyone deserves the harsh comments.
It’s easy to categorize things and people and belittle them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I aim to do short articles here, and the inspiration spawns from
advice I’m asked and discussions I have. I am much more positive
or nuanced in real life but I seldom take time here for the usual
disclaimers. This blog post is my overall disclaimer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note my posts are more intended as warnings (you think X but
please check Y) than attacks: I don’t wish to fall in the “cynicism
makes you look smart”, but rather to warn people about blunders or
unnecessary hardships they can avoid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to learn these the hard way, and I wish you don’t.
I know most lessons only stick when learnt the hard way,
so here’s for my optimism: I hope that you learn anyway :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think my willingness to not hide ugly truths even when I have
interests in comfortable lies happening are a huge part of why people
not only come to me for advice, but come back for followups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, the very first blog post reminds these ideas are mine, open to
debate and possibly wrong. I am willing to change my mind.
Whenever I felt I must be negative: please prove me wrong! :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/09/13/forgive-negativity.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/09/13/forgive-negativity.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Policy on referrals</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I don’t take any kind of money or presents for referrals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people ask me for referrals because of my position as a co-organiser
at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/ParisRB&quot;&gt;ParisRB&lt;/a&gt;,
hence I think it should all go back to the ParisRB community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is: if you give money to ParisRB you’ll be listed
as a sponsor, which is good for more exposure and finding hires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also communicates your engagement: you have funds,
and you are ready to spend them for things you need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not noble, it is merely logical and efficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;most people will try to give me a present from 10 to 300€&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;most people would pay recruiters or head-hunters from 2000 to 9000€&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ParisRB’s job board, events, or sponsoring would cost 100, 300, to 1500€&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if you end up sponsoring us, we’ll be glad to explain how to
present your speech or job offer so as not to throw this money away,
and increase your chances to get the greatest developers :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 10 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/09/10/policy-on-referrals.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/09/10/policy-on-referrals.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bothering my network</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As a developer and as &lt;a href=&quot;http://rubyparis.org&quot;&gt;ParisRB&lt;/a&gt;’s organiser,
I often get asked to pass on offers to “my network”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I have a
&lt;a href=&quot;/2015/09/10/policy-on-referrals.html&quot;&gt;policy on that&lt;/a&gt;
too often with &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/series/#partner&quot;&gt;red flags&lt;/a&gt;,
but let’s suppose it’s not the problem here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is a network? What is yours? What can you do with it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your network is just a loose set of LinkedIn connections gained
through business cards exchange and knee-jerk reaction to connect,
you cannot ask these people anything:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they won’t remember you and your proposal has no weigh&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they will have no second thoutght in blocking you if you spam&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they won’t get up for you at 3AM in the morning like you’re their best friend&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or it can be a network of trust. You are skilled, a connector, or
both. You don’t chase people, people chase you because they know you
always have good things in store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this position, forwarding low-value things is a reputation killer.
Forwarding a valued thing that you do not endorse might too: like
giving a birthday cake that’s not fitted to the recipient’s taste; or
rotten/poisonous dessert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s like retweeting some witty word and finding out the author or the
twitterer have very opposing political views from your own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forwarding shouldn’t mean strict endorsement, but the whole experience
is nonetheless attached to the forwarder: his honesty, trustworthiness
and respectability are at stake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To forward anything, you should then do actual and painstakingly long
and hard research on offers you get. You probably don’t have time for
all of these, so you will often have to cut those who are not clear
enough upfront, and, well… recruiter is a full-time job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me rephrase what you ask of me when you want to use “my network”:
you’re asking me to spam my friends, and people I took a long time to
build trust with, and forward an offer with
&lt;a href=&quot;/2015/07/19/mystery-offers.html&quot;&gt;so little information&lt;/a&gt;
I simply risk to lose that quality network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks, but no thanks.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/09/03/bothering-my-network.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/09/03/bothering-my-network.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>I won&#39;t pay for quality</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“I don’t care about quality.”
Is that really the signal you want to send?
There are so many subtle ways you might lose your target on this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a developer and as &lt;a href=&quot;http://rubyparis.org&quot;&gt;ParisRB&lt;/a&gt;’s organiser,
I often get asked&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for senior devs referrals, and then told the team is all junior coders&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if I can refer young developers ready for production code (I call them “seniors”)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if I know someone to untangle a mess done by waves of interns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good developers are expensive, so we devs tend to hear this as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I want cheap coders&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I won’t train them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I don’t really care for quality&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re trying to recruit a good developer, this is a red flag:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;will you pay me?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if I need something to work, will you pay for it?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if I need something, will I get the high-end or low-quality?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, it’s perfectly fine for a company to grow and to have
chosen tradeoffs in the past, that you’d like to change by now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not saying you’re doomed and there is something you can do about it: &lt;b&gt;there is hope!&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you happen to raise this kind of red flag, please be clear about
it, communicate the story that led there, your intent and possibly
your plan to get out of this soon[1]. 
Or you’ll just look like so many other exploiters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] it’s fine to say you need that senior dev to give you inputs,
actually even if you have a plan I hope you’re ready to change it
from inputs from that person you’re hiring to help.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 30 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/08/30/wont-pay-quality.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/08/30/wont-pay-quality.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Job offers go both ways</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I see a huge lot of offers where the employers think they are very
clear on what they want, but not nearly as much on what they offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;entrepreneurs&quot;&gt;Entrepreneurs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a developer to even bother contacting you regarding your offer,
you probably need some proofreading to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;put yourself in the others’ shoes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;add how your teams and decisions work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;add a salary range (we KNOW it’s negociable)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;add your Joel Test maturity level&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And add whatever makes you better than others.
If you don’t have such points, you have other things to worry about than hiring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will likely have to remove mentions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;are you sure you need or even want what you listed?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;that inadvertently discriminate or alienate huge parts of the population.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;why the schoolyears? Lousy engineers exist, as do amazing autodidacts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;anything that others use, either abusive or non-discriminatory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, why some precise technologies? Good engineers can learn. 
For Rails jobs, I would rather hire an expert on Python or Java MVC
than an expert on non-web Ruby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hires&quot;&gt;Hires&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re going for a job interview. Yes, you’ve probably been trained
to be on the begging side, to just be happy to have a job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But you are going to spend more of your waking hours at work
than with your family, friends or significant others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can’t hurt to research or grill the prospective company with
questions.  And if you can’t find any of your own (really?) there are
some ready for you, written on the excellent Joel Spolksy and aptly named:
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/fog0000000043.html&quot;&gt;the Joel Test&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 23 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/08/23/bidirectional-communication.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/08/23/bidirectional-communication.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>MicroSF</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;help&quot;&gt;
   Inspired by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MicroSFF&quot;&gt;@MicroSFF&lt;/a&gt;
   Twitter account (SF in 140 chars), I tried to make some. That&#39;s pretty hard!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The alien arrived in a dangerous zone.
“Bring it to safety, quick!” Jovians said.
“Sulfur storm? They’re killing me!” Zhāng shouted. #μSF&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“How many worlds did you discover?
- Just yours: the other videos are other people in the same space suit.”
Li was no longer their hero #μSF&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“How do semitranslucent walls work?
- it’s just visual FX on the video, to show what’s inside.”
The Aliens didn’t need us &amp;amp; wiped Earth #μSF&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Aliens invited human ambassadors.
The travel made them claustrophobic, the FTL jump crazy &amp;amp; sick.
They died. We declared war. #μSF&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zhao finished the time machine.
Just a few seconds later, just a quick test.
It worked, but Earth was many miles away.
Horror, briefly. #μSF&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 13 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/08/13/microsf.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/08/13/microsf.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Transformation orga</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;On m’a récemment demandé mon avis sur la mise en place
d’une méthodologie et les outils employés.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Je me suis rendu compte en écrivant ma réponse que cela pouvait
s’appliquer à tout outil organisationnel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bienvenue dans : la mise en place de l’outil X.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Je ne pense pas qu’une stratégie top-down fonctionne bien pour transformer
et continuer quoi que ce soit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quand chaque N+1 (leader local) a sensibilisé ses équipes au besoin X
et son importance, il a commencé la transition culturelle. Ses équipes
et lui permettront alors, par opposition ou par exemple, de fournir un
retour d’expérience intéressant aux N+2, aux équipes voisines etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cloisonner le X à un “département X”, une “équipe de X”, un rôle
“responsable X”… est le meilleur moyen de créer un “eux et nous”, de
faire passer les “X” pour des gens pénibles qui empêchent les autres
de travailler et qui se drapent dans une aura indûe de “dernière
bêtise à la mode qu’un escroc a réussi à vendre aux patrons et pour
lesquels on vient probablement de dépenser dix fois l’argent qui nous
aurait permis de sortir la tête de l’eau avec ne serait-ce qu’un
stagiaire de plus”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Une démarche bottom-up, grassroot me semble alors indispensable pour
tout projet qui veut 1) se lancer et 2) durer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Et mon avis sur X ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Par les individus et leurs expériences, dans les différentes équipes
de mon entreprise, de mon client principal et de nos autres
partenaires, nous sommes probablement à des étapes différentes sur la
voie de sensibilisation ou de mise en place d’outils organiques de X :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;on sent la friction sans pouvoir nommer le besoin de X&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;on fait déjà du X sans le savoir via nos outils et méthodes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;on connaît le mot et les concepts du X&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;on connaît les outils leaders et on veut les mettre en place&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;on est en process de mise en place de X&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;nous sommes à l’état de l’art de X&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;nous dévions des enseignements du X car nous avons vu ses limites et le faisons à notre sauce&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;À l’inverse, ceux qui se présentent avec un département, un outil, une
charte sans avoir la culture et la preuve que X est dans l’ADN de vos
équipes, me semblent voués à l’échec&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Si vous voulez enterrer un problème, crééz une commission.”&lt;br /&gt;
Prouvez-moi que votre process n’est pas un &lt;a href=&quot;https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Culte_du_cargo#Le_culte_du_cargo.2C_m.C3.A9taphore_et_th.C3.A8me&quot;&gt;Culte du Cargo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/08/09/un-nouvel-outil-organisationnel.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/08/09/un-nouvel-outil-organisationnel.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Recruiters&#39; Vicious Cycle</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Many developers hate recruiters but can’t explain why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We like laws, logic, systems and hacking them. It is simply a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Market_for_Lemons&quot;&gt;Market for lemons&lt;/a&gt;
problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s my take on what makes for a vicious cycle:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;as middlemen they only get paid if the job contract is signed through them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;as hires or employers we would like to get most of that mystery out&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this blind process makes everyone wary and suspicious&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;as a result, a recruiter needs to get more and more devs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they don’t have enough time for each, and forgo quality checks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;employers then prefer to use several recruiters for one opening&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;one developer will then get called by many recruiters,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;as every company with open job offers will get called too&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this becomes more and more of a volume thing, not quality&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;some recruiters find dirty tactics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;everyone has to follow or die&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;many developers hate recruiters&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;developers try to find jobs without recruiters&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;back to #1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve seen many recruiting companies adressing a few of these points in
hopes of breaking the whole cycle. I wish them the best to grow and
destroy every single step of this vicious cycle, but it often falls into
a case of #10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As employers, I think you can only act on #1 and #6: choose one
recruiter and stay with him wherever the hires come from. This will of
course mostly mean you hire a recruiter in-house instead of giving
exclusivity to a single recruiter cabinet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course some will say this simply means getting rid of recruiters.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/07/26/recruiters-cycle.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/07/26/recruiters-cycle.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mystery Offers</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Would you recommend a restaurant you’ve never been to, or a book you didn’t read?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a developer and as &lt;a href=&quot;http://rubyparis.org&quot;&gt;ParisRB&lt;/a&gt;’s organiser,
I often get asked to pass on offers to “my network”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common problem is simply that I’m not given relevant information.
Why would I simply spam my friends with things I don’t know a thing about?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I get that most of these offer come from recruiters, and as middlemen
they only get paid if the job contract is signed through them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m very sorry about this &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/07/26/recruiters-cycle.html&quot;&gt;vicious cycle&lt;/a&gt;,
but I need at least:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to know the company and business model (fame and ethics)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;location (commute is a significant happiness modifier)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;expected work conditions (remote, time off…)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to meet the current team (mandatory in the process, great as an opener)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;your philosophy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how your hiree will be managed, how expectations are set and checked&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;opportunities for growth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course you should (or are legally required to) avoid exclusive language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might want to remove whatever the others are adding by default:
yes, we all want dedicated, motivated, skilled autonomous, self-improving workers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also want coworkers who wash themselves and do not assault others,
but that’s never mentioned as it should be obvious.
So it’s not really what makes you different, right? Skip it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, on salary range, some say don’t mention it, most
say you should. The key here is: most people know it’s open for
negociation, especially seniors, so that won’t make them flee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should’t go for “depending on skills and previous experience”
though, since everybody writes that. How about the very inclusive
“feel free to apply even if you don’t meet all the requirements”?
Men usually are not stopped by it, but many women are.
So this will explain your salary range’s width, AND be inclusive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So: upfront salary or not? I’d say:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;don’t worry, a large range is fine ($x-yK with y &amp;gt; 2*x is fine)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;or just explain: $xK for juniors, $yK for seniors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;or simply better: post two openings, one for juniors and one for seniors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 19 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/07/19/mystery-offers.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/07/19/mystery-offers.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
