<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sylvain Abélard</title>
    <description>Sylvain Abélard - talks, events, blog, projects, translations...
</description>
    <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://maitre-du-monde.fr/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jul 2015 16:16:36 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Jul 2015 16:16:36 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sociologie et développeurs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http:&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;pixelastic.com&quot;&gt;Tim Carry&lt;/a&gt; est un développeur et prend des
notes des nombreux &lt;a href=&quot;http:&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;meetups.pixelastic.com&quot;&gt;meetups&lt;/a&gt; auxquels
il assiste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparemment mon talk sur &lt;a href=&quot;https:&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;speakerdeck.com/abelar_s/effects-of-sociology-on-devs&quot;&gt;“Quelques effets de la sociologie appliqués aux développeurs”&lt;/a&gt;
lui a beaucoup plu et au lieu d’un résumé il a écrit une &lt;a href=&quot;http:&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;meetups.pixelastic.com/2015/06/09/humantalks-juin-2015/#sociologie-applique-aux-dveloppeurs-a-namesocioa&quot;&gt;transcription détaillée&lt;/a&gt;
de la plupart des effets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Devant la masse de travail j’ai également contribué à l’article sur son blog
en ajoutant notes de pied de page et liens pour en savoir plus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Je ne suis pas toujours d’accord avec quelques raccourcis et certaines
interprétations, et j’ai parfois ajouté mon grain de sel, mais j’ai
évité de modifier ou retirer son point de vue : il est intéressant de
voir comment cela a été perçu, et je suppose qu’une autre partie de
l’audience aura tiré d’autres enseignements encore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Merci pour son travail qui ajoute énormément à tous ceux qui n’ont pas pu assister
au talk ou qui voudraient s’y replonger en format texte !&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/07/09/sociologie_devs.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/07/09/sociologie_devs.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Responsibility</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;You can’t be responsible of everything. &lt;br /&gt;
It’s tiring when you are or feel so, and we’ve heard all sorts of advice to “let it go”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when you think everything depends on you,
you strive to be the best, to learn more, to act more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The high expectations you set on yourself make you, temporarily, a more miserable person. &lt;br /&gt;
But the efforts you make then make you a better person in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t discard responsibility.
You ask for forgiveness for screwing up things that were only 10% your fault.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You look dependable. You make friends and allies for the next tough moment.
Foes and abusers jump out from the shadows, so you know who they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course you need to rest from time to time.
Step aside, explain your new friends that cost you, and you need to rest.
They’ll understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when you’re done resting, become awesome again and improve yourself faster again.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/06/07/responsibility.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/06/07/responsibility.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Inequal Partner</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I have several ongoing series about recruitment:
&lt;a href=&quot;/2015/05/03/gullible-young.html&quot;&gt;Gullible Young&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;/2015/05/17/looking-for-partner.html&quot;&gt;Looking for dev partner&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see many words in job offers looking for a partner,
using words that convey strong inequality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a super-idea businessman talking to a just-a-tool developer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You will be a probationary partner&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I don’t get your world, and I don’t want to&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’m looking for a partner because I can’t pay&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’m not confident this idea will pay soon enough&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I didn’t make the effort of understanding you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, really: come to meet us first in a relaxed setup, watch and listen.
It’s as simple as: get respected by respecting others.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 May 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/05/24/the-inequal-partner.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/05/24/the-inequal-partner.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hard to find good devs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We are hackers. We make things. And:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We often already have our dream job&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You’re probably not offering their dream job&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We have ideas of our own, why work for yours?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You either have an edge in business, or not&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We have heard your story many times it got old&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So devs are hard to get, and you should be different.
Nobody would buy your product if you were just the same as the other, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When looking for a partner, you’re selling your product, your company and yourself.
Use your marketing smarts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 May 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/05/20/hard-to-find-good-devs.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/05/20/hard-to-find-good-devs.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Looking for dev partner</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As a developer and organiser of &lt;a href=&quot;http:&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;rubyparis.org&quot;&gt;ParisRB&lt;/a&gt;, I often get
asked if I want to be a partner in a new startup adventure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I’m already a partner and already in an adventure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You probably already know:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2015/05/20/hard-to-find-good-devs.html&quot;&gt;it’s hard to find good devs&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the devs you find are available for a reason&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you probably can’t judge a developer’s skill&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you’ve put up a job offer which:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;is the same as every other we get each week&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2015/05/24/the-inequal-partner.html&quot;&gt;uses words which do not convey equality&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;or words easily mistaken for abusive&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;might just be looking for a &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/05/03/gullible-young.html&quot;&gt;Gullible Young&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then you ask me for referrals, but:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I probably don’t have enough info to bother them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;repeatedly bothering one’s ‘network’ loses it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;top-talent referral is worth a lot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do wish you the best of luck and hope we all grow the community.
Companies with hiring problems will turn to other technologies which is not in our best interest either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not doing this to repel you or to sound like a passive-agressive smartass.
I will be glad to help if only… you help me helping you.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 May 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/05/17/looking-for-partner.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/05/17/looking-for-partner.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>You&#39;re no CTO</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is my series on the &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/05/03/gullible-young.html&quot;&gt;Gullible Young&lt;/a&gt;.
I don’t mean to mock them, I’ve been one.
They’re often lovable with their dreams and energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, you’re the CTO?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re the only dev in the company, you’re not the CTO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re the developer, and someone is giving you a glittering title
so you will work for him for cheap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sorry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also possible you’re given full freedom to build great things.
That’s awesome!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there’s a reason why they say devs want three
things “autonomy, mastery and purpose”, and the one you’re missing
here is having mentors to grow or peers to compare and grow with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You probably will enjoy your job long enough until youth’s pride wears
off and you feel you’re missing something (with or without realizing it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By then, I hope your company has grown enough to give you more challenges,
hire senior coworkers, or even provide you with a tech lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before feeling betrayed, consider this from your partners:
it may not feeling you’re not up to the task, it may not be ingratitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, it’s opportunity, and it’s yours to seize.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/05/13/youre-no-cto.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/05/13/youre-no-cto.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>You&#39;re no manager</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is my series on the &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/05/03/gullible-young.html&quot;&gt;Gullible Young&lt;/a&gt;.
I don’t mean to mock them, I’ve been one.
They’re often lovable with their dreams and energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, you were promised a managing position?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, be grateful of course, this might be a white lie to get you in.
After all, young graduates are sought after and they’ve all been
implanted the idea that managing is great and coding is dirty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But please put your ego aside and read on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you’re a bright genius, will 50-somethings listen to you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you live, see, and manage enough crises in a company setting
so someone is confident enough to give you the lead on such situations?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or will you just be updating spreadsheets for someone more important?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you need the job and can’t do something else, that’s fine.
If you actually have enough experience (associations, internships, gigs), that’s fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But please don’t think you &lt;em&gt;deserve&lt;/em&gt; to be a manager.
No one owes you nothing until you deserved it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people fought harder than you to get here.
I’d rather give them that kind of position.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/05/10/youre-no-manager.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/05/10/youre-no-manager.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Stay late, get pizza</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is my series on the &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/05/03/gullible-young.html&quot;&gt;Gullible Young&lt;/a&gt;.
I don’t mean to mock them, I’ve been one.
They’re often lovable with their dreams and energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, you stayed very late and the company paid for pizza?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, be grateful of course, someone might care about you, and it
might be the only thing they can do within the budget the company
allows them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And perhaps you stayed late because you did some horrible mistake, or
you slacked off during the day, or you have very flexible hours, or
you’re just having fun coding when nobody’s disturbing you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re willingly spending time (not your health, this isn’t worth it)
away from your passions and your loved ones, please do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But these also are basic manners. Or a way to cut you from seeing
friends who might tell you how abusive your employer is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, be aware of what your market hourly rate is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re getting 15€ worth of dinner when you give the company four
hours at 50-100€/hour, you’re just being ripped off.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 May 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/05/06/stay-late-get-pizza.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/05/06/stay-late-get-pizza.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Gullible Young</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The Gullible Young are a valuable resource to the IT ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Individually they’re worth nothing, and managers like that they are so cheaply replaceable.
But as a whole they represent a workforce that’s silent and easy to abuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very simple way to keep them helpless is distracting their young minds with absurdities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Everything is an emergency!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The customer is always right!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do insane hours!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You’ll be a partner!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2015/05/10/youre-no-cto.html&quot;&gt;You’ll be the CTO!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2015/05/10/youre-no-manager.html&quot;&gt;You’ll be a manager!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;2015/05/06/stay-late-get-pizza.html&quot;&gt;And they’re happy when they work very late and the company pays for pizza.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re young, a valuable life lesson is “trust, but verify”.
No one should be offended if you want to check what’s really in the job offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might rationalise your choice (Stockholm Syndrome) by some things you’re learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you’re not paid enough to be living honestly and decently, leave.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you’re not growing, have time to learn or others to compare, leave.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you don’t have time to see friends, loved ones, or do hobbies, leave.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 03 May 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/05/03/gullible-young.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/05/03/gullible-young.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Self Wiki</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This blog is also an experiment in my values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should link them all to each other, “Wikify” all these views to find
contradictions, paradoxes, and dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’d be an enlightening, probably difficult, possibly life-changing experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then it’d be interesting to run some algorithms: graph traversal,
topological sort, PageRank…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These would output what are the principles I think apply to the most
situations, or the roots of the problems and behaviours, or the ones I
hold the dearest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If something already exists for this, I’d be glad to know :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 26 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/04/26/selfWiki.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2015/04/26/selfWiki.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
