<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sylvain Abélard</title>
    <description>Sylvain Abélard - talks, events, blog, projects, translations...
</description>
    <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://maitre-du-monde.fr/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2017 13:55:16 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2017 13:55:16 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.4.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Validating phone numbers</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;dont&quot;&gt;DON’T&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except blank (empty or filled with space/tab characters),
just keep the format people want you to store:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;France likes spaces or dots, groups of two 01.23.45.67.89&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;UK likes groups of three 01 23 456 789&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Services in the US like mnemonics like 01234-PIZZA&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Validating numericality will remove all of these:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;01 23 45 67 89 -&amp;gt; 0123456789 (legibility)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0800 123 123 -&amp;gt; 0800123123 (123.123 is more memorable than 12.31.23)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0800 42 42 42 -&amp;gt; 0800424242 (0800 means free number, French people like it better than 08.00)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0800 1 PIZZA -&amp;gt; KO or 0800174992 (there are gems to find mnemonics IIRC)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a shorter phone number that’s inside a company’s office -&amp;gt; KO&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;foreign number: +49 (0) 123456789 -&amp;gt; KO&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;special numbers like 911 -&amp;gt; KO&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t always say that, but: trust people, not code ;)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2017/03/08/phones.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2017/03/08/phones.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Letting your project</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;You set up a great community, but life happens, it’s time to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, thanks for what you did. Setting up things that work, especially with humans,
is hard, demanding and often thankless. You could have done nothing, but you did.
You might learn, hours or years after you left, how people liked what you did.
Pat yourself on the back, you deserve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, how would you set the transition up? Well, like a normal project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What makes you want to quit?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it non negotiable, like moving away? Will you regret it, like a bruised ego thing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it “just” that you burned out? Perhaps you can just step down:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I will only keep being a leader if someone helps me with [XXX]&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I will not be the leader, but I would help anyone who takes over by doing [YYY]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people don’t want to be a leader, but are willing to help.
What can you ask the community, that would keep you helping them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What does it take to take over?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What were you doing in that “job”?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What would the next person need to know or do?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How many hours did you spend weekly? Should we expect rushes?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do most project require hard work or just letting momentum going?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What help would you provide to someone who could takeover but is not sure yet?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you contacted the leaders in each kind of task there is, each “sub-project”?
Explain this, ask and answer the questions together, and see if they’re willing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you’re a little bit more ready for the next steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;let it go without regret: it was too hard to keep going and you tried your best&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;actually, things aren’t so bad, you are simply reshaping the organisation and your role&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 04 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2017/03/04/associations-takeover.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2017/03/04/associations-takeover.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Remote Mentor</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hard problem ahead? Want me to help?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well I’m willing to, but I will not give you the answer ;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I want to know from you are these:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;context&lt;/strong&gt; - what do you have now? where are you?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;goals&lt;/strong&gt; - where would you like to go?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feel lost already? Not sure? No problem, continue telling me more about, we’ll sort this out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you can’t answer, that’ll be hard for both of us. Calm down, tell me more, and it’ll work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I want to try out now are these:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;plan&lt;/strong&gt; - what steps could we take, to solve this?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;action&lt;/strong&gt; - what next step can we take right now?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s OK for you not to have these answers. It’s why you needed a mentor for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if you tried things before, I want to know. Perhaps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it was a nice try, you missed just a little bit&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you had the first part right, the rest is just not fitting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you went into a dead end, because you missed something&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I’m glad you tried. We’ll discuss that and fill in the blanks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps you’ve tried to do these steps on your own, and succeeded by now?
Well, that’s awesome, now the merit is all yours :D&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2017/01/22/remote-mentor.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2017/01/22/remote-mentor.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Copy Pasta</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;del&gt;Never&lt;/del&gt;Don’t &lt;ins&gt;just&lt;/ins&gt; copy-paste code.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are learning code, you are stuck. 
You can be either hasty, frustraded or both. 
I understand and absolve you from all this, but please, don’t “just” copy-paste code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve seen questions on the Internet (forums, IRC, Slack,
StackOverflow…) that were obviously exercice for school or program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no shame in asking questions, but in the short attention-span
world that is Internet, what you will likely get are answers that are
each ugly in a way:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;magic tricks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;convoluted code&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ill-fit habits from other languages&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;library or gem your teacher will disapprove&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so your call for help will bite you in the back: lose you right
now, teach you bad code habits, and give the illusion that the problem
is solved, when your understanding clearly isn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plus, these exercises are likely easy to find all over the web, so why ask it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want you as a junior dev to be an excellent searcher.
This will give you the basic words, which you will find in the doc/ref.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over years, this habit will give you awesome “problem solver” skills,
strong basics, and a coworker I’d love to be with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking for recipes is fine as long as you cross-check and make sure
that every line you copy (which is not a sin) is well understood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and take the time to read the whole page, but here’s short excerpt:
http://catb.org/~esr/faqs/smart-questions.html#homework&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(sorry, ESR wrote it, it’s kind of offensive and dated, but still a good reference)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go now! I get that you have no time and plenty of fun to have elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that wasn’t too patronizing, really not the intent,
but I’ve seen too many juniors “broken by StackOverflow/Slacks”.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2017/01/21/copy-pasta.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2017/01/21/copy-pasta.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fable Voyageurs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;J’ai lu une histoire de ce genre au primaire.
J’ai tenté de trouver la source, mais je ne trouve que ça :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;http://www.pitt.edu/~dash/traveltales.html#twotravelersandfarmer&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alors voici ma transcription, de mémoire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Un voyageur arrive devant une ville, et voit un vieillard assis.
“Bonjour ! Peux-tu me dire quel genre de gens sont les citoyens de cette ville ?&lt;br /&gt;
— comment étaient-ils d’où tu viens ?&lt;br /&gt;
— agréables, honnêtes et accueillants : j’y avais beaucoup d’amis, et je suis triste de les avoir quittés&lt;br /&gt;
— tu trouveras les mêmes ici”&lt;br /&gt;
Le jeune homme entre dans la ville, heureux.&lt;br /&gt;
Puis un autre voyageur arrive.&lt;br /&gt;
“Bonjour ! Peux-tu me dire quel genre de gens sont les citoyens de cette ville ?&lt;br /&gt;
— comment étaient-ils d’où tu viens ?&lt;br /&gt;
— menteurs, voleurs et désagréables : à dire vrai, je suis content de les avoir quittés.&lt;br /&gt;
— tu trouveras les mêmes ici”&lt;br /&gt;
Le jeune homme passe son chemin.&lt;br /&gt;
Un autre qui passait par là demande au vieil homme :&lt;br /&gt;
“mais, c’est incroyable, tu leur as dit complètement l’inverse à l’un puis l’autre !&lt;br /&gt;
— non, je leur ai dit la même chose.”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2017/01/20/fable-voyageurs.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2017/01/20/fable-voyageurs.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Self skill assessment</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“I’m learning to code, when will I be good enough to get a Junior-level job?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a question I get a lot in my tech communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three keys for me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TRUST&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SKILL&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TASKS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SKILL&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can I guess what my “skill level” is?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can do plenty of job interviews, and see what people want, what you like, and how much they offer you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can show up with MOOCs’ certificates or shipped software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can stalk people or companies you want to work with/for, guess or ask what they need, and work on this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or you can use any list of skills. Here are three tips:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Programmer Competency Matrix
http://sijinjoseph.com/programmer-competency-matrix/&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why Rails is hard (a list of skills you should have)
https://www.codefellows.org/blog/this-is-why-learning-rails-is-hard/&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Any company talking about their Open Salary or Compensation Policy
Of course, Joel Spolsky made his point long ago:
https://www.joelonsoftware.com/2000/08/30/fog-creek-compensation/&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2017/01/15/skill-assessment.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2017/01/15/skill-assessment.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>No trolling</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I don’t like the word “troll”, as in “internet trolling”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people use this word for many wildly different things.
As developers or philosophers, we know good naming is hard, and we know bad naming creates pain (Camus).
Please use the correct word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style&gt;dl dd { font-weight: bold; }&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2016/10/07/cynicism.html&quot;&gt;Cynicism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;You're probably being inconsiderate, or not helpful.&lt;/dt&gt;

  &lt;dd&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2017/01/10/dark-humour.html&quot;&gt;Dark humour&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;You have better things to do than being a smartass.&lt;/dt&gt;

  &lt;dd&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2017/01/09/fake-news.html&quot;&gt;Fake news (aka Lies)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Making things up for fun is cool until someone believes it&lt;/dt&gt;

  &lt;dd&gt;Harassment&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;That's simply not done.&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, you like trolling ? Do you really like calling yourself one of these things?
Are you taking pride in calling yourself something that’s definitely bad and definitely not yourself?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to be clever and provocative, please do, I love it!
But make sure you’re doing it cleverly, or you’ll be looking just like an angry idiot, or worse.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2017/01/11/no-trolling.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2017/01/11/no-trolling.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Dark Humour</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I like to laugh at absurd things, of which Life provides plenty.
I kinda like dark humour. But it’s dangerously close to pitfalls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve had more than my share of &lt;a href=&quot;/2016/10/07/cynicism.html&quot;&gt;cynicism&lt;/a&gt;,
which hasn’t led me to much good. Neither for me, nor for others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dark humour usually has the same problems: it “passively allows” for actual harm.
Some people will be as smart as you and see the snark. Some won’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other people will simply see that saying harmful things is OK.
It’s irrelevant whether they understand or not, if it’s a joke or not.
Things will escalate, and soon enough there’ll be some uncomfortable things.
Will you be able to stop them then? Will you have driven good folks out?
Where should the line be drawn?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is actually &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/How_to_Win_Friends_and_Influence_People#Fundamental_Techniques_in_Handling_People&quot;&gt;the very first tip&lt;/a&gt; in Dale Carnegie’s “how to win friends and influence people” (cheesy title, good tips).
Some biographies will stress out how some remarkable person never spoke foul of anyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a teenager, one usually don’t need to add to snarkiness and ego.
As an adult, when raising a problem, it’s better, more responsible to bring at least one solution.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2017/01/10/dark-humour.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2017/01/10/dark-humour.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fake news</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It looks like 2016 has been hectic for many.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many things happened, many debates were made, many sub-debates were added…
Much information and many comments were shared, losing many of the signal in the noise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Confusion, outrage, overreaction… this plays all too well in our
reptilian/fight-or-flight and primate/social brains:
new, shiny, loud things all over the place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also easy to lose oneself, one’s time, and one’s mental health in all this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a problem with underreaction too!
The word “normalization” was all over the place in my Twitter timeline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://duckduckgo.com/?q=we+don%27t+change+our+minds+even+with+evidence+of+the+opposite&amp;amp;t=ffab&amp;amp;ia=web&quot;&gt;all well known&lt;/a&gt; that we prefer information we already like, and disregard the rest.
So it’s not a surprise that we have &lt;a href=&quot;https://duckduckgo.com/?q=why+people+believe+fake+news&quot;&gt;a tendency to believe fake news&lt;/a&gt;. The more we are aware of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_cognitive_biases&quot;&gt;our many cognitive biases&lt;/a&gt;, the more we should fight the urges to let them rule us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As citizens, or as humans, we have a duty to others: to be informed and to act.
I feel we have a duty to look for truth, to keep a healthy skepticism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a fast-moving world, where jokes or propaganda are re-shared by people in power,
we have a duty to check the most dubious things, and not share until we check.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the burden should not be on us. Well, no one will take it, so now it is ours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press and ethics in press have always struggled: they should write what people buy,
but they should print what people don’t want printed (“or it’s not press but PR”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And by the way, I would have said the previous quote is from Orwell.
But I checked, and there seems to be no evidence for that misattribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, well.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2017/01/09/fake-news.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2017/01/09/fake-news.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tech coaching</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Prenons une équipe de développeurs et un projet qui vont mal.
Ça va ensemble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En général, cette équipe n’a pas le temps de s’auto-améliorer ou de faire des sujets de fond.
Les personnes jouent en permanence aux pompiers sur les problèmes les plus “brûlants”.
On croit qu’on n’a pas le temps de faire des tests ou des refactorings,
donc on continue une méthode visiblement mauvaise,
et on n’essaie apparemment pas de s’améliorer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Si les chefs sont trop fermés, ou pieds et poings liés, difficile à dire.
Mais imaginons qu’ils se disent “comment pouvons-nous nous améliorer ?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certains prennent un coach, un mentor, un senior… mais embaucher c’est cher, alors on prend un consultant.
Là encore le consultant peut être mauvais, on n’étudiera pas ce cas ; imaginons que ce soit une personne formidable et compétente.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Une des parties les plus intéressantes de cette prestation… est la définition de cette prestation.
Le manager qui accepte, les “leads techniques actuels internes à la team” et le “coach / lead tech externe partiel”,
vont cadrer la prestation : argent, heures, calendrier…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;La loi de Conway nous dit que l’humain impacte la technique et réciproquement, justement par les points
que l’on organise et que l’on considère comme importants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Par exemple, j’ai testé ces 4 choses-là et ça marche super bien :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;on fait une classroom entre devs 2h par semaine&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;on va faire un point d’archi sur ce qui est dur à comprendre pour l’expliquer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;on va faire une revue de code sur un bout de code parce que telles habitudes sont horribles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;on va augmenter la couverture de test ensemble&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;L’avantage est que la charge de nouvelles choses à absorber est 1h par semaine de cours + 1h de pratique :
pas trop pénible pour les devs, pas trop handicapant pour la “vitesse” actuelle, ni trop cher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Si les devs sont réceptifs, on peut augmenter la qualité en permanence (et le coaching peut presque s’arrêter).
Si les devs sont pas réceptifs, on peut arrêter assez tôt.
Et du coup il suffit de signer pour 3 mois (12 demi-journées), ça n’est pas un engagement très cher,
et on peut reconduire si #1 ca marche + #2 les devs en redemandent.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 14 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/12/14/part-time-tech-lead.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/2016/12/14/part-time-tech-lead.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
