<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sylvain Abélard</title>
    <description>Sylvain Abélard - talks, events, blog, projects, translations...
</description>
    <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://maitre-du-monde.fr/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2015 21:49:33 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2015 21:49:33 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>

    
      <item>
        <title>The Best Code Ever</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A novice was attending a presentation by the newly-appointed master &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Zjing&quot;&gt;Zjing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a heartfelt oration about the sacred duties of the few people
who could code or chose to, she asked everyone to do their best,
not only at their work, at honing their craft, but also on working
to make the world a better place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“These topics are expected from a new master,
but they feel as pointless as teenage’s chatter.
We live remotely from the world high in our mountains.
Small, lonely, fallible and mortal.
How could one achieve that?” wondered the nun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She resolved to see other masters for advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The novice asked master &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Kaimu&quot;&gt;Kaimu&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;br /&gt;
“This humble nun would like to know how she can do her best
to change the world for the better. Would you enlighten me?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kaimu replied: “By coding one line at a time.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The novice asked master &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Bawan&quot;&gt;Bawan&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;br /&gt;
“This humble nun would like to know how she can do her best
to change the world for the better. Would you enlighten me?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Banzen replied: “By removing one line of code at a time.”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>2015-03-01</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/cases/00a.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/cases/00a.html</guid>
        
        <category>code</category>
        
        
      </item>
  
      <item>
        <title>Kiss</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A nun came puzzled to master &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Banzen&quot;&gt;Banzen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I heard we should keep things simple.
Yet we pride and feed ourselves by dealing with complexity.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Said Banzen:
“Indeed, we should deal simply with our customers’ complexity.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Said the nun:
“I have seen customers ask simple things, deeming them complex,
and complex things that seemed simple to them.
How can we not lose our heads?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The master replied:
“Complex needs not be complicated.
What is simple to the herder is confusing to the smith ;
What is obvious to the smith is unknown to the herder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If the nun wishes to speak about any craft,
including and especially her own,
she has to learn the language of his customer,
talk to each one with his own words,
and make sure the code explicitly reuses those words.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At that moment, the nun envisioned how her knowledge of the customer
would be sealed in the code, for every later monk to grasp both
code and the customers’ trade when opening the file, whatever
length of time would pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overjoyed at the idea, she kissed the master goodbye.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>2015-03-06</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/cases/00b.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/cases/00b.html</guid>
        
        <category>kiss, communication, domain, DDD</category>
        
        
      </item>
  
      <item>
        <title>Open roads</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A novice came to master &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Bawan&quot;&gt;Bawan&lt;/a&gt;.
“What is the most important thing to master in Computer Science?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Replied the master: “The oldest common denominator,
for it will survive us as it has survived the assaults of time ;
History will enlighten you about what has been, so you can judge what will be.
Indeed, learn about the low-level bits,
for if you despise them they will byte you back.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A monk came to master Bawan.
“What is the most important thing to master in Computer Science?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Replied the master: “The most common recipes,
for we all have to read others’ code, and they ours ;
understanding the common patterns helps you understand without reading every single line.
Indeed, learn about the flaws and edges of each pattern,
for each context will require a different tradeoff.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A senior monk came to master Banzen.
“What is the most important thing to master in Computer Science?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Replied the master: “The most abstract thing,
for we labor every day on abstractions, and need to share them ;
you need to make every intention obvious even to the novice, or your own memory.
Indeed, learn to compare languages, frameworks, principles, or methods,
for each abstraction freely chosen today is our shackles of tomorrow.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A nun was standing nearby, and couldn’t help but notice the answers are different.
“Three monks came with the same question, yet the answer changed each time. Why?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Replied the master: “Learning is a path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This young monk is dizzy with too many roads.
I chose for him a well-traveled path so he gets challenged but not lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This monk is getting too confident walking a few paths again and again.
I sent him exploring so he comes back with experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This old monk is comfortable enough with many roads.
I sent him where there is no path, so he might make one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This lesson is what I now deem the most important in Computer Science,
and rests well out of Computer Science’s domain:
code is done by people, and only by understanding them and their flaws
can we rely on the code their brains and hands produced.”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>2015-03-11</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/cases/00c.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/cases/00c.html</guid>
        
        <category>CS, low level, patterns, abstractions, learning, teaching</category>
        
        
      </item>
  
      <item>
        <title>Lasting discipline</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A novice came to the scribe &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Qi&quot;&gt;Qi&lt;/a&gt; asking:
“Pardon my imprudence, but a question troubles my mind.
Can I speak privately to you?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The old scribe replied:
“Speak your mind, young one, I am here to help.
But my position enclines me to sharing:
if your question has any use to anybody else in the temple,
I should write about it for future generations.
So why must that be private?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Well,” said the novice, visibly uncomfortable, “it’s about the masters.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They are known to be harsh,” conceded Qi, “but fair.
No correction has been admonished where there needn’t be.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Then which master’s discipline do you believe has had the most lasting impact on the Temple?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Qi pondered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“My fallible memory needs a refreshing from my trustful archives.
Come to me tomorrow.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The novice bowed and went out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following day, the novice came by.
From his unassured steps it could be guessed that he wondered
if he was about to find the masters in the scribe’s study,
and have a cryptic lesson be taught to his body rather than his mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He found no such thing, but the scribe was a pity to see:
“Ah, young friend! I’m sorry I had to stay up all night
and have not found a satisfying answer yet. Please come next week.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The novice bowed and went out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next week, the novice came to find Qi.
He was surprised to see the scribe waiting for him, four big piles
of books, sheets and scrolls on his crowded desk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The old scribe waved at each of them as if inviting to read each of
them to prove each of his points, or to justify the amount of sleep
lost to the task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Master &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Kaimu&quot;&gt;Kaimu&lt;/a&gt; is most renowned for his discipline.
No error is brought to him without receiving proper treatment.
Though some monks hid errors from him for fear of seeing their carreer or life ended prematurely,
I believe many errors have been avoided in fearing his most definitive lessons.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Master &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Banzen&quot;&gt;Banzen&lt;/a&gt; is most famed for seeking perfection.
He is relentlessly sought after, and sets up time for knowledge sharing.
Though some believe it a weakness when he seems sad and resigned,
I believe his hard work and corrections brought enlightenment to many monks.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Master &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Bawan&quot;&gt;Bawan&lt;/a&gt; is most known for his lessons.
He always find metaphors that stick to the head, sometimes litterally.
Though some would think it’s a weakness when comparing to the others,
I believe his most memorable corrections bring long-term value to our Temple.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Master &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Suku&quot;&gt;Suku&lt;/a&gt; is most revered for her judgement.
Her corrections spread to more than just one person, and she corrects even the masters.
Though some thinks the time she sets aside for novices might be wasted,
I believe ensuring both teaching, and continuously spreading the lessons
is a great service for generations at the Temple.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The novice pondered Qi’s stories.
“So you’re saying I should go with master Suku?
It’s a shame she left for a long trip.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Qi swiftly threw a huge book with metal corners to the novice.
Taken aback by this reaction, he did not make a move and the heavy tome
hit him hard in the stomach, temporarily depriving him of his breath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What I’m saying,” replied Qi, “is that each of these methods
work more on some people, and each reinforce the others by
providing comparison of the others’ strengths and weaknesses.”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>2015-03-16</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/cases/00d.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/cases/00d.html</guid>
        
        <category>teaching</category>
        
        
      </item>
  
      <item>
        <title>The forgotten monk</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Un moine à la compétence inutile
Grimpeur / creuseur de montagne
… Pas de montagne&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;[33&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Fear]&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2015 21:49:33 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/cases/00e.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/cases/00e.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
  
      <item>
        <title>What&#39;s an object?</title>
        <description>
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2015 21:49:33 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/cases/00g.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/cases/00g.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
  
      <item>
        <title>Planning and Acting</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Two recently appointed abbots &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Aki&quot;&gt;Aki&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Haru&quot;&gt;Haru&lt;/a&gt;
were assigned to their teams and projects.
Due to the recurring shortage of abbots at the Temple&lt;a href=&quot;#note-*&quot; id=&quot;noteref-*&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
they were given much freedom in choosing their ways of leading
despite their young age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They were also led by a healthy dose of righteousness,
foolishness, and most of all the wish of not losing one’s head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon arriving to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Spider Clan&quot;&gt;Spider Clan&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Aki&quot;&gt;Aki&lt;/a&gt; immediately
launched several projects at once, redirecting the monks from
previous tasks. “The Emperor is waiting for us”, he said,
“and he is not famous for his patience.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surely, this would please the Province Governor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Haru&quot;&gt;Haru&lt;/a&gt; scoffed at this attitude: he immediately
set up the guidelines, the meetings and documents that
should be produced before working, like &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/case/154&quot;&gt;True Engineers&lt;/a&gt; should.
“Once we deliver applications to the Emperor, their failure
is ours. No surprises to him, nobody among us surprisingly
losing his head.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surely, this would please the Temple’s masters,
and upon her return master &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Suku&quot;&gt;Suku&lt;/a&gt; would find a cleaner abbey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to his knowledge on the ways of the Temple,
the old monk &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Shinpuru&quot;&gt;Shinpuru&lt;/a&gt; was asked to help on many projects,
and he soon found himself having to answer orders from two
heads at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As gardening was soothing his mind, he asked master &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Banzen&quot;&gt;Banzen&lt;/a&gt;
for the permission of creating two shrubs.
The master mercifully agreed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first garden did not show any sign of improvement for weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aki had difficult deadlines to meet, and required full
attention from his monks. He came find the senior monk one evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shinpuru was sitting before it, silently contemplating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You asked for two plots, yet you let this one untouched”, noted the abbot.
“What purpose are you seeking?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Planning,” said Shinpuru.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second garden was quickly sowed with a mix of whatever
Shinpuru could find. Many kind of flowers were blossoming,
but one could recognize weeds that would steal the other
flowers’ nutrients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haru had a big overhaul to do, and required full attention
from his monks. He came find the senior monk one evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shinpuru was removing some of the plants in no particular order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You are pulling today the flowers you sowed last week,” noted the abbot.
“What purpose are you seeking?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I changed my priorities, and like this colour better”, said Shinpuru.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both abbots returned to their quarters with stronger faith in their own ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Qi&#39;s poem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tell two people the same thing &lt;br /&gt;
they can hear two things &lt;br /&gt;
depending on previous faith.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;footnote&quot; id=&quot;note-*&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;#noteref-*&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp; As documented in cases &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/case/61&quot;&gt;61&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/case/62&quot;&gt;62&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/case/67&quot;&gt;67&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/case/104&quot;&gt;104&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/case/120&quot;&gt;120&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/case/179&quot;&gt;179&lt;/a&gt; and probably a few others besides. Abbots in the Spider Clan have the average life expectancy of a rice bowl before a starving novice.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>2015-03-21</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/cases/01a.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/cases/01a.html</guid>
        
        <category>management, planning</category>
        
        
      </item>
  
      <item>
        <title>Action, reaction</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The young abbots &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Aki&quot;&gt;Aki&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Haru&quot;&gt;Haru&lt;/a&gt; had known each other for
a few years as novice monks, and were eager to prove their
methods were better than their rival’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The old monk &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Shinpuru&quot;&gt;Shinpuru&lt;/a&gt; was working on many projects and found
himself working under the order of both junior abbots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Master &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Zjing&quot;&gt;Zjing&lt;/a&gt; heard of this and came by to form an opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Good evening, monk,” she said.
“I’ve never seen you in these gardens before.
Would you tell me a word on our newest abbots?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Good evening, master,” Shinpuru replied bowing politely.
“Both abbots have very little in common but their eagerness
and motivation. For this I am grateful, and thanks to their
example I found the motivation to start cultivating these
two additional plots recently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This first plot I set out after Haru’s example.
After much work of planning, leveling, ploughing, weeding,
I’ve endured criticism for there was no plant to please
the monks’ eyes. Now I planted grass on it:
it’s perfectly cut and requires minimal maintenance.
Nothing will ever get out of control, which is for once relaxing.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commented Zjing: “It is indeed a picture of quiet and order,
and I will enjoy sitting on fresh grass this spring for my
morning meditations.
It is a shame you had to endure criticism while working.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This second plot,” added Shinpuru leading her to the opposite
of the courtyard, “is more fitting with Aki’s nature.
As soon as I got my hands on it, I added big, colourful flower
bushes, and have kept changing ever since.
Some of the flowers die, but others prosper and grow,
even though I kept adding even more plants.
Growing in that competitive environment, the offspring are strong
and I’m eager to see what this garden can teach me.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commented Zjing: “It does look a bit messy but 
these bright colours mixes most certainly please my eyes.
Everywhere I look I can see delighting details in your work.
But would you leave this unattended, don’t you fear weed would
upset the delicate balance and overtake your garden?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shinpuru thanked Zjing, bowed, and left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was still standing before the second garden,
wondering what correction or praise the two young abbots deserved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>2015-03-26</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/cases/01b.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/cases/01b.html</guid>
        
        <category>management, time to market, processes</category>
        
        
      </item>
  
      <item>
        <title>Watch and punish</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Newly appointed master &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Zjing&quot;&gt;Zjing&lt;/a&gt; was settling into her position
in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Spider&#39;s Clan&quot;&gt;Spider’s Clan&lt;/a&gt;. A few things had changed with the
arrival of young abbots &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Aki&quot;&gt;Aki&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Haru&quot;&gt;Haru&lt;/a&gt;, each taking
strong control on the methods of the teams they were assigned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They knew the most dangerous times would be right upon their arrival,
when their new method would first be slowing down the team as they
adjusted, and the young abbots wanted to prove themselves and
please their masters most quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed the Chief Abbot was asking Zjing what she thought
of the junior abbots, so he would know what to teach them
next, and if necessary how to correct them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zjing told him to come in the courtyard at dusk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a hard day of labor, the old monk &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Shinpuru&quot;&gt;Shinpuru&lt;/a&gt;
was rounding up his day by tending to the two shrubs
he was given.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Good evening, old monk,” said the Chief Abbot.
“How is it going with the two young abbots we sent you?
I heard you have projects in the care of each of them,
so surely you will be able to compare and comment.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Please come see my two gardens,” was Shinpuru’s only reply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chief Abbot was already thinking Shinpuru fool and lazy,
and as he was ready to mock the old monk, an eye at
Zjing’s stick and menacing eyes hinted him to say
nothing and bow his agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Passing the first garden, the Chief Abbot noted
“It is a fine lawn, its order pleases me, but there is
nothing of note to say here.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The same can be said of Haru,” replied Shinpuru.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Passing the second garden, the Chief Abbot noted
“It is a beautiful, if messy flowerbed.
I can see potential in this one, if kept under tight control.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The same can be said of Aki,” replied Shinpuru.
“Though I’m not sure about control.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Are you not the gardener? Don’t you bend Nature to your will?”
was the Chief Abbot’s reply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A few of these details are of my own doing,” said Shinpuru.
“But most are Nature’s hand at work. I would be foolish
to deem myself the leader of these flowers, nor would have
I managed to create such beauty if I had an idea at first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If I wanted to stick to this idea, I would have felt miserable
in trying to preserve a plan that couldn’t work.
Instead Nature showed me the way.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chief Abbot was still silently pondering these words
when Zjing thanked Shinpuru, bowed, and left for the night.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>2015-03-31</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/cases/01c.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/cases/01c.html</guid>
        
        <category>management, planning, control</category>
        
        
      </item>
  
      <item>
        <title>Strict and Lax</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Young abbots &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Aki&quot;&gt;Aki&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Haru&quot;&gt;Haru&lt;/a&gt; were each given a team
of developers to lead on several projects despite their young age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of them was foolish enough to devote themselves to a certain approach,
but they were not so young as to believe in magical Silver Bullets,
and kept being humble except to one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This would in the long term reduce the need for more patches on patches ;
for some of the standalone applications were only asked to bypass faulty
applications, leading to duplicate codebase, reinventing the wheel,
and creating data which would lead to inconsistencies in
the legacy applications.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2015 21:49:33 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/cases/01d.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/cases/01d.html</guid>
        
        <category>management, planning,</category>
        
        
      </item>
  
      <item>
        <title>Switch</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Aki&quot;&gt;Aki&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/#00b&quot;&gt;delivered results fast&lt;/a&gt;, but was still
losing ground to all the needs that were absolutely required
immmediately, or even preferably for yesterday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monks under his rule were often working late or during weekends.
As this showed no signs of slowing down, some began to call in sick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Haru&quot;&gt;Haru&lt;/a&gt; was more prudent, and his teams were and willing to take
the blame for not accepting all the requirements, or delaying some.
Better by far, he said, to produce only one perfect application
than lose focus and disappoint customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was soon accused of letting the monks becoming lazy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2015 21:49:33 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/cases/01e.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/cases/01e.html</guid>
        
        <category>management, planning,</category>
        
        
      </item>
  
      <item>
        <title>Stick and carrot</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Zjing demande son avis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Landhwa aime Haru.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wangohan n’a pas encore empoisonné Aki.
Car la rigueur lui plaît, mais les décisions sont motivées par
le process. Si Aki disparaît, le Process reste sur les prochains abbés.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Djishin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haru reçoit tous les jours le low-hanging fruit. A bit ripe.
Aki reçoit un excellent repas après une semaine de jeûne.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2015 21:49:33 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/cases/01f.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/cases/01f.html</guid>
        
        <category>management, planning,</category>
        
        
      </item>
  
      <item>
        <title>Switch</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Aki&quot;&gt;Aki&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/#00b&quot;&gt;delivered results fast&lt;/a&gt;, but was still
losing ground to all the needs that were absolutely required
immmediately, or even preferably for yesterday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monks under his rule were often working late or during weekends.
As this showed no signs of slowing down, some began to call in sick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Haru&quot;&gt;Haru&lt;/a&gt; was more prudent, and his teams were and willing to take
the blame for not accepting all the requirements, or delaying some.
Better by far, he said, to produce only one perfect application
than lose focus and disappoint customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was soon accused of letting the monks becoming lazy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon arriving to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Spider Clan&quot;&gt;Spider Clan&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Aki&quot;&gt;Aki&lt;/a&gt; immediately
announced the monks would be rated on &lt;i&gt;quantity&lt;/i&gt;: how many
lines of code were produced, tickets completed, standalone
applications produced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surely, this would please the Emperor and Province Governor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/names/Haru&quot;&gt;Haru&lt;/a&gt; scoffed at these rules: his was the
way of &lt;i&gt;quality&lt;/i&gt;: he immediately set up the guidelines, the meetings
and documents that should be produced before working,
like &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecodelesscode.com/case/&quot;&gt;True Engineers&lt;/a&gt; should.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2015 21:49:33 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://maitre-du-monde.fr/cases/01g.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maitre-du-monde.fr/cases/01g.html</guid>
        
        <category>management, planning,</category>
        
        
      </item>
  
  </channel>
</rss>
